<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://joaomarques.website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-14T16:43:59+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml</id><title type="html">João Marques | Abxy</title><subtitle>UX/UI Designer &amp; Frontend developer. Author of the gaming blog ABXY.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Played this month – November 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-nov-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – November 2024" /><published>2024-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-nov-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-nov-24">&lt;p&gt;As expected, November was for the most part a month dedicated to the latest Atlus magnum opus, Metaphor: ReFantazio! However, as usual, there was some time to squeeze a few smaller games in between. So, without further ado, here’s what I’ve been playing:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in time, with 60 hours clocked in, I think I’m near the end of the game. At least it’s what the game’s calendar tells me, as I’m currently heading into the last month, from a total of five. Still, comparing with a Persona game this one feels more streamlined, which is a good thing since it was my main issue with &lt;em&gt;Persona 5 Royal&lt;/em&gt;. I have so many things to say about this game, most of them good, but I’ll save for an eventual review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Undertale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a game that I had for a long time in my list. Looking for a quick break from &lt;em&gt;Metaphor&lt;/em&gt;, I decided it was the ideal time to play it. I think &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; needs no introduction, as its a quintessential indie game. Created mostly by a single person, quirky, inventive and with a great sense of humor. In it, we play as a human who falls into the underworld, where the monsters live, and our goal is to escape it. During our journey, we discover the truth about the underworld and the long standing conflict between humans and monsters, as we meet the most absurd and charismatic characters. Seriously, the writing of this game is its strongest asset, with its music coming in a close second. I finished the game in around 6 hours, but since it’s so short, I’ll play it again in the future to see its “good ending”.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Sonic R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / Sega Saturn
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sequence of the Sega Saturn 30th anniversary, I was challenged by a colleage from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@TheGamesTome&quot;&gt;The Games Tome&lt;/a&gt; to do a “Deep Dive” review of &lt;em&gt;Sonic R&lt;/em&gt;. Since it made years since I last played it, I decided to pick it up again to have a fresher perspective on it. This game is from a weird era in videogames, when the developers were still figuring out how to work with the third dimension, as so, its controls are everything but conventional. We control Sonic and some of the other characters in its universe, racing in 5 circuits with many hidden paths and secondary challenges. So far so good. But when we pick up the controller, we quickly understand that this isn’t quite a racing game, neither a platformer. It’s something in between. The first minutes are truly awful, but by the end, (as in, one hour later) when we finally understand its mechanics, it actually becomes fun and engaging. Lastly, it’s impossible to talk about Sonic R without mentioning its fantastic eurodance soundtrack. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XWoekUxnZ7w&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can you feel the sunshine?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Bomb Rush Cyberfunk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fan of &lt;em&gt;Jet Set Radio&lt;/em&gt; I had this game under my radar since it was announced, but its steep price, for an indie game, made me forget it for a while, until now. I finally got it during this last Nintendo eShop “black friday”, in a sweet 50% discount deal. Being completely honest, from what I’ve played so far, I was expecting more. Sure, the music and style are top-notch (all they had to do was to copy &lt;em&gt;Jet Set Radio Future&lt;/em&gt; sense of style though), but the gameplay could be better, and the camera isn’t amazing either. Keep in mind that these are only early impressions. My opinion might change later on. Let’s see.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that was November! With 2024 almost done, the next edition of this series will be the last one, as I’ll change the format starting next year. I’ll save the details for January. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">As expected, November was for the most part a month dedicated to the latest Atlus magnum opus, Metaphor: ReFantazio! However, as usual, there was some time to squeeze a few smaller games in between. So, without further ado, here’s what I’ve been playing:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1 year of ABXY</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/1-year-of-abxy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1 year of ABXY" /><published>2024-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/1-year-of-abxy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/1-year-of-abxy">&lt;p&gt;As you guessed by the title, this week marks one year since I released the &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/welcome-to-abxy&quot;&gt;first post of ABXY&lt;/a&gt;! The idea was to release this post on the exact day, but well, let’s just pretend today is December 2nd. In that post I shared my vision for this project, and after &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy-posts&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;32 posts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I can say it turned out to be pretty much what I had in mind - a place where I can document and share my opinions of all the games I play, be it in a review format or via something more casual, such as the “Played this month” rubric.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A lot happened during this time - not all related to games, but let’s stick with that for the context of this post - as I learned how hard it is to run a blog. At least I improved my writing skills and speed as a consequence. Part of the difficulty was my perfectionism and “impostor syndrome” always getting in the way, but even looking back at everything I wrote, I’m happy with the end result.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s do now a retrospective, going through the good, the bad and also some key events of this first year of ABXY!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-good&quot;&gt;The good&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-still-standing-after-a-year&quot;&gt;It’s still standing after a year&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s right! It might not look like a big achievement, but it took some perseverance to keep posting, especially during periods where I had less availability to do it, or my “creative juices” were running low. By this point this is my longest running side project ever, and I want to keep increasing that record.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;writing-is-becoming-easier-with-time&quot;&gt;Writing is becoming easier with time&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons for me to start ABXY was precisely to improve my writing skills and so far I can say that goal is being achieved. For you to have a better idea of what I’m talking about, the first review I ever did went through several revisions (I can’t specify how many, but let’s assume more than 4 or 5) until it reached its final version, while the most recent was done in a couple of hours, without any re-writing needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bad&quot;&gt;The bad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lack-of-consistency&quot;&gt;Lack of consistency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By far the hardest part of running a blog is to keep posting quality stuff regularly, and that’s one of the main problems of ABXY. Sadly it’s the only one that I don’t imagine getting much better without a bigger time investment, something that’s practically impossible for me at this moment.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;not-that-many-readers&quot;&gt;Not that many readers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this blog is in part a way for me to log my gaming activity, I would be happy if other people also read and enjoy the stuff I write. Since the beginning I already got great feedback from various sources, for which I’m very thankful. But apart from that, the engagement with the content is very low. To be fair, I did nothing to change that, but I intend to. By the way, this blog has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; if you want to be notified each time I post something new. I hereby invite you to follow it!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;almost-non-existent-divulgation&quot;&gt;Almost non-existent divulgation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This point is directly related to the previous one. If people don’t know about the blog and its posts, it’s obviously difficult for them to read them. The occasions where the blog had more views was precisely when I divulgated it on my Instagram, &lt;em&gt;Marketing genius, I know!&lt;/em&gt; I simply have to be more consistent on that, otherwise, all this effort in writing reviews and opinions with a pinch of personality is not totally wasted, but a bit in vain.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-events&quot;&gt;Key events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gamescom-2024&quot;&gt;Gamescom 2024&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to Germany to attend one of the biggest gaming conventions in the world was absolutely fantastic, even if very exhausting. I even did a post back then, &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24&quot;&gt;documenting my experience there&lt;/a&gt;. This Gamescom also marked the first time I participated in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B0MnYMpNpT8&quot;&gt;The Games Tome podcast live stream&lt;/a&gt;, precisely to give my first-hand impressions of this year’s event.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-games-tome&quot;&gt;The Games Tome&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, &lt;em&gt;The Games Tome&lt;/em&gt; is a long-standing Portuguese podcast about video games from every era, covering everything retro, as well as the current news and releases, with a fantastic cast and community. For years I was a regular listener and participant, via chat, in their Sunday night live streams. A few months ago I was invited to participate in a spin-off episode that consisted of a deep dive review of Persona 5 (which was &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; game of the year of 2023&lt;/a&gt; if you remember). Since then, I started to participate in the main episodes as well, as the fifth member of the main cast. So far it has been amazing being part of this incredible podcast, even if my Monday mornings have become a bit rough because of it (as we usually end the stream around 1-2am) but to be honest, the sacrifice is totally worthwhile. You can follow the podcast on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@TheGamesTome&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; and on audio streaming platforms such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/2qphywGobVNkB5BRF1lxMW?si=e9a4da5258964d66&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/in/podcast/the-games-tome/id1639802857&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border-radius:12px&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/show/2qphywGobVNkB5BRF1lxMW?utm_source=generator&amp;amp;theme=0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;152&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VesBcuhVrkg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ An episode of the podcast dedicated to the 30th anniversary of the Sega Saturn.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that was the first year of ABXY, quite an eventful one if you ask me. I hope in a year’s time I’m here once again to celebrate its second anniversary. Until then, thank you very much for keep reading my gaming-related ramblings. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">As you guessed by the title, this week marks one year since I released the first post of ABXY! The idea was to release this post on the exact day, but well, let’s just pretend today is December 2nd. In that post I shared my vision for this project, and after 32 posts I can say it turned out to be pretty much what I had in mind - a place where I can document and share my opinions of all the games I play, be it in a review format or via something more casual, such as the “Played this month” rubric. A lot happened during this time - not all related to games, but let’s stick with that for the context of this post - as I learned how hard it is to run a blog. At least I improved my writing skills and speed as a consequence. Part of the difficulty was my perfectionism and “impostor syndrome” always getting in the way, but even looking back at everything I wrote, I’m happy with the end result. Let’s do now a retrospective, going through the good, the bad and also some key events of this first year of ABXY! The good</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sonic X Shadow Generations</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-x-shadow-generations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sonic X Shadow Generations" /><published>2024-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-x-shadow-generations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-x-shadow-generations">&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing to think how much has changed since 2011, when the &lt;em&gt;Sonic Generations&lt;/em&gt; was originally released. Back then, the blue hedgehog’s public perception was way worse than it is today, with a couple of games of questionable quality preceding it to blame for. It was without surprise that when &lt;em&gt;Generations&lt;/em&gt; came out, being incredible as it is, it felt like the second coming of Christ, becoming without much doubt an instant classic.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The situation is quite different now in 2024. SEGA did a brilliant job these last few years with the franchise, not only with the most recent games and compilations (for the most part), but mainly with everything else, such as merchandise, TV shows and movies, making Sonic more relevant than ever for the mainstream culture. It’s precisely in that context that &lt;em&gt;Sonic X Shadow Generations&lt;/em&gt; appears - a remaster that initially didn’t look more than an easy way to promote the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Sonic 3&lt;/em&gt; movie, where Shadow will be prominently featured. For the surprise of everyone, it turned out to be much, much more than that. This is truly the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonicthehedgehog.com/yearofshadow/&quot;&gt;“Year of Shadow”&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-much-to-remaster&quot;&gt;Not much to remaster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who never played Sonic Generations before and have no idea what I’m talking about, let me explain it. This game was essentially a huge celebration of the series’ history - being released to celebrate its 20th anniversary - recreating some of its best stages, from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nZzlcI_2adk&quot;&gt;Green Hill Zone&lt;/a&gt; (Sonic The Hedgehog, 1991) to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bpzx24qV2_w&quot;&gt;Planet Wisp&lt;/a&gt; (Sonic Colors, 2010). A well crafted game combined with the nostalgia factor was a recipe for success.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The concept of remastering &lt;em&gt;Sonic Generations&lt;/em&gt; might be a bit silly, considering how good the original game still looks like nowadays, but there was always a chance for things to go wrong, like it happened in the past with &lt;em&gt;Sonic Colors Ultimate&lt;/em&gt;, ported by a third party and launched in a terrible state. This time around SEGA didn’t risk and put the original developers, as in, Sonic Team, in charge.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The result was magnificent. Sonic Generations is here in all its glory, but now with improved resolution, textures and framerate! Besides that, all the cutscenes’ dialogs were apparently re-recorded to include more references to the previous games’ events. This was totally unnecessary but it perfectly reflects the effort put on this.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CDmVayEU76w&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The announcement video introduced Shadow as a third playable character, beside Modern and Classic Sonics.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-new-shadow-campaign&quot;&gt;The new Shadow campaign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s talk about the real star of this release. When you boot the game, you are presented with two separate options: Sonic Generations or Shadow Generations. The first is what I described in the chapter above, a remaster of the original release. The second is an entire new campaign with a distinct gameplay and stages. Obviously I jumped immediately to this option once I got the game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shadow’s story, while it overlaps with Sonic’s one, is quite unique. Much more dark and sad, fitting for the character. Here Shadow, much like Sonic on its side of the story, gets stuck in a weird time loop and is able to revisit past events, which means more reimagined stages! Since Shadow was introduced in 2001’s &lt;em&gt;Sonic Adventure 2&lt;/em&gt;, the first stage featured is precisely from that game, with other notable inclusions being Kingdom Valley from the infamous &lt;em&gt;Sonic’06&lt;/em&gt; and Chaos Island from &lt;em&gt;Sonic Frontiers&lt;/em&gt;. Actually this last one doesn’t make much sense canonically, since Shadow doesn’t appear in &lt;em&gt;Frontiers&lt;/em&gt;, but honestly I don’t care, because the stage and its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qg3ICBuzM_o&quot;&gt;remixed soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; are awesome.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speaking on &lt;em&gt;Frontiers&lt;/em&gt;, a game that I absolutely adore despite its shortcomings, it’s very clear that it served as a backbone for this &lt;em&gt;Shadow Generations&lt;/em&gt;. Here we also have an “open zone”, where we can not only navigate between stages, but also run freely while collecting the many random tokens spread around by completing small environmental challenges. Obviously Shadow’s open zone is more condensed than the vast islands of &lt;em&gt;Frontiers&lt;/em&gt;. Probably because of that, exploring it becomes a bit tiresome after some time. Frontiers’ influence is also felt in the gameplay, with Shadow being very responsive to the player inputs, just like in that particular game. This was something that I only realised when I jumped back to Sonic Frontiers and had an hard time readjusting to the more floaty controls of that game. With that said, both gameplay styles are fine, but if I had to choose one, it would be Shadow every day.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Atd6Xvzs7W8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ One of the best stages of Shadow Generations is based on Sonic The Hedgehog (2006), one of the most infamous games in the series.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonic Generations is great as it was 13 years ago&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadow Generations isn’t just a bonus, but an entire new game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadow’s gameplay precision is arguably the best in the entire series&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazing new reimagined stages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadow Generation’s open zone can become a tad repetitive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonic’s controls feel a bit floaty in comparison with Shadow’s
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic X Shadow Generations is a masterclass in how to remaster and re-release a beloved game, by updating it to today’s standards and bundling it with an even better new one!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">It’s amazing to think how much has changed since 2011, when the Sonic Generations was originally released. Back then, the blue hedgehog’s public perception was way worse than it is today, with a couple of games of questionable quality preceding it to blame for. It was without surprise that when Generations came out, being incredible as it is, it felt like the second coming of Christ, becoming without much doubt an instant classic. The situation is quite different now in 2024. SEGA did a brilliant job these last few years with the franchise, not only with the most recent games and compilations (for the most part), but mainly with everything else, such as merchandise, TV shows and movies, making Sonic more relevant than ever for the mainstream culture. It’s precisely in that context that Sonic X Shadow Generations appears - a remaster that initially didn’t look more than an easy way to promote the upcoming Sonic 3 movie, where Shadow will be prominently featured. For the surprise of everyone, it turned out to be much, much more than that. This is truly the “Year of Shadow”. Not much to remaster</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – October 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-oct-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – October 2024" /><published>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-oct-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-oct-24">&lt;p&gt;What a month, people, what a month! October was monumental in terms of new releases. We had a new Zelda (technically it came at the tail end of September, but I ended up playing it mostly in October), we had Metaphor: ReFantazio, we even had an exceptional Sonic game (or should we say Shadow game?)! And I’m only mentioning the ones that resonate with me, there were even more great games coming out. Anyway, here’s what I’ve been playing:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of those games that I played non-stop until the end, without getting tired of it for a bit. That by itself is a great demonstration of its quality. I had my issues with it though, but for that, read the full review of the game &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metaphor is finally out! In true Atlus fashion, this looks like a game to last many dozens of hours, so expect me to talk about it for even longer than I already am. For now, with 18 hours clocked in, I can only say that I’m loving it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Need for Speed Unbound&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a long-time NFS fan, I was interested in Unbound since I saw it for the first time. Unfortunately it didn’t come out for last-gen consoles, so now that I have Xbox Series X I decided to finally try it out. So far, my experience is being mostly positive, but I have a couple of complaints about the progression and AI behavior during the races. But I’ll save them for a full review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Die Hard Trilogy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Light-gun shooter / PS1
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in Madrid this last month and I took the opportunity to do a tour through the city’s amazing retro gaming stores. One of my acquisitions was a light-gun for the PS1. My hope was to play &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OZsUNE9I9Mc&quot;&gt;Time Crisis&lt;/a&gt;, but I soon realized my gun wasn’t compatible with it. Luckily there was another game in my collection that was, being it precisely this Die Hard Trilogy. Actually the shooting section is only one of the three different gameplay styles it has to offer, each one themed after a different movie, thence the “Trilogy” in the title. While still inferior to Time Crisis, I had a good time with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Sonic x Shadow Generations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic fans, we’re feasting! As someone who played and liked very much Sonic Generations back in the day, I had reasonable expectations for this re-release as &lt;em&gt;Sonic x Shadow Generations&lt;/em&gt;. What I wasn’t expecting was for the brand-new Shadow Generations game to be my favourite part of the compilation, by far! I want to write a review for it soon, but I’m still pondering if it deserves the “Masterpiece” rating or not. Either way, it’s the closest thing to a perfect 3D Sonic game we ever had, in my opinion.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Grand Theft Auto: Stories from Liberty City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Xbox 360
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve finished the second and last expansion included in this compilation - The Ballad of Gay Tony - where we play as the right-hand/bodyguard of the nightclub entrepreneur Tony Prince, who is, of course, also involved in many illegal activities. One of those is the selling of some stolen diamonds that goes horribly wrong and escalates to epic proportions. In terms of gameplay, this expansion has much more variety than anything else in the GTA IV universe, with a big focus on skydiving, helicopters and boats. Storywise, I feel like this expansion had potential to be a full game, as some particular points were a bit rushed because of the smaller number of missions, in comparison with GTA IV’s main story.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for October! For next month, well, probably even more Metaphor: ReFantazio. I’ll tell you then.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">What a month, people, what a month! October was monumental in terms of new releases. We had a new Zelda (technically it came at the tail end of September, but I ended up playing it mostly in October), we had Metaphor: ReFantazio, we even had an exceptional Sonic game (or should we say Shadow game?)! And I’m only mentioning the ones that resonate with me, there were even more great games coming out. Anyway, here’s what I’ve been playing:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom" /><published>2024-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom">&lt;p&gt;It’s not very common in the long-running Zelda series for a game to be announced and released almost out of the blue, yet that’s exactly what happened with &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;. Only one short year after the monumental and highly anticipated &lt;em&gt;Tears of the Kingdom&lt;/em&gt;, Nintendo decided to announce this game, for the surprise of everyone - at least from my understanding. From the get-go, it was clear this would be a simpler game than its predecessor, marking a return to the series’ 2D gameplay style. However, that didn’t mean it was more of the same - quite the opposite, in fact. After all, it was the official debut of the titular princess as a protagonist - considering Nintendo refuses to acknowledge the existence of the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M52zKfu-cHk&quot;&gt;Philips CD-i games&lt;/a&gt; that also had Zelda as the playable character. From my experience, it was a meritorious debut, but with some glaring issues on its execution.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-power-of-wisdom&quot;&gt;The power of Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the lore of the series, princess Zelda is the triforce of Wisdom’s bearer and this game made sure to honour that. Unlike Link, Zelda isn’t equipped with a sword and shield, but with a magical rod. With it, we can create copies of various objects found in the world, known as &lt;strong&gt;Echoes&lt;/strong&gt;, and use them to overcome challenges, whether reaching specific locations or defeating enemies. For the former, we can use echoes of boxes, trees, trampolines, beds, and even blocks of water. For combat, we can “fight fire with fire” by creating echoes of the enemies themselves. Obviously is not that simple, with some of them requiring a bit more creativity to defeat, but there’s some satisfaction in doing it purely by brain power and not brute force. This is by far the biggest change in paradigm present in Echoes of Wisdom, with the difficulty coming more in form of mental puzzles and less in mechanical skill. And of course, having Zelda save Link - rather than the other way around - marks another change for the series status-quo.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Apart from the main character skillset, everything else is quite familiar to someone who played a Zelda game before. The most interesting aspect of it in my opinion is the blend of concepts between the traditional 2D games of the series and the open world ones (Breath of the Wild, Tears of the Kingdom), bringing elements from those such as a mission log, quick travel portals spread across Hyrule, unlinear progress (although much more toned down) and even cooking recipes.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/01onjjAUnOQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ A quick overview of Zelda's abilities in Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;echoes-of-issues&quot;&gt;Echoes of issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all the elements this game takes from its predecessors, there is one that’s much more evident than anything else. Back in 2019, Nintendo released a remake of the Game Boy classic &lt;em&gt;Link’s Awakening&lt;/em&gt;, in a completely new art style that resembled a diorama made with plastic pieces, looking almost like a Playmobil set. While initially strange, this aesthetic proved to work well once we acually the game. For &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;, they decided to reuse the exact same style, but this time I found myself less impressed. Though charming, this style has creative limitations that lend a somewhat cheap aspect to the game - something difficult to explain in objective terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can explain objectively however is the terrible framerate the game has most of the time. This was already a problem in the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Link’s Awakening&lt;/em&gt;, that was also developed by the team behind this one, but here it gets even worse. By default it targets 60fps, but it can only reach them consistently in indoor environments, such as dungeons. While navigating through Hyrule, it rarely hits that target, sometimes going down to 20fps or even less. Sure, the Nintendo Switch is by today’s standards a very limited machine, but many games released for it proved that when well optimized, they can look and perform exceptionally well. &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt; should have been one of those cases, but unfortunately it isn’t.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zelda as a protagonist for a change!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Echoes mechanic is quite fun to play with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It borrows the best of the open-world 3D titles structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awful framerate drops while exploring the overworld&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toy-like aesthetic gets a bit old by the end of the game
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom is a worthwhile entry in the iconic series, successfully blending old and new elements. However, its technical issues and over-reliance on a limiting art style prevent it from reaching the heights of some of its predecessors.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">It’s not very common in the long-running Zelda series for a game to be announced and released almost out of the blue, yet that’s exactly what happened with Echoes of Wisdom. Only one short year after the monumental and highly anticipated Tears of the Kingdom, Nintendo decided to announce this game, for the surprise of everyone - at least from my understanding. From the get-go, it was clear this would be a simpler game than its predecessor, marking a return to the series’ 2D gameplay style. However, that didn’t mean it was more of the same - quite the opposite, in fact. After all, it was the official debut of the titular princess as a protagonist - considering Nintendo refuses to acknowledge the existence of the infamous Philips CD-i games that also had Zelda as the playable character. From my experience, it was a meritorious debut, but with some glaring issues on its execution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – September 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – September 2024" /><published>2024-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V-_crlOw0HA&quot;&gt;Ooo wee&lt;/a&gt;, September, am I right? During this month I was able to finish the games I was playing last month and also to have a glimpse into October and the new games that come with it. September 2024 was also the month where I finally jumped into the next generation of consoles, or is it &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; generation, since it’s already almost four years old? Anyway, I got an Xbox Series X, which also had some impact on the games I played.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a game! It’s all I have to say now that I finished it. Expect a full review of it soon. I still have no idea of what I want to say about it, but I’ll get there eventually.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of reviews, I’m also done with Persona, however my opinion about this one isn’t as positive. You can already read my review &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Lego City Undercover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was something that I had for many years in my purgatory of unfinished games. I don’t even know why I abandoned it in the first place, as it isn’t a very long game to begin with, except if you decide to collect everything. Since I have better ways to waste my time, I decided to focus mostly on the main story. Overall it was a fun game, but nothing to write home about.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Grand Theft Auto: Stories from Liberty City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Xbox 360
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated in the intro paragraph, I just got an Xbox Series X. But as typical of this generation, I got the system but no games for it. However, this was nothing but a big brain plan from my side to test the backwards compatibility with Xbox 360 games, starting with GTA Stories from Liberty City, which is a standalone compilation of the two GTA IV expansions. I already finished the first one, The Lost and the Damned, but I still have the second one to play. In terms of gameplay, well, it’s more GTA, but with different protagonists. The true highlight here is the 60fps boost from playing it on the Series X. &lt;em&gt;Chef’s kiss.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio (Prologue Demo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to have a glimpse of what will become of my gaming life until the end of this year, at least, by starting my journey in the highly anticipated Metaphor: ReFantazio. This is one of those demos that let you carry the save data to the full game, once it’s out by October 11th. So, if you are into RPGs and have a PC, PS4, PS5 or Xbox Series, please try this. It’s all I ask. It costs you nothing, except time. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right at the tail end of the month, a wild new Zelda game appears! This time around we actually play as Zelda, who can replicate an innumerable amount of objects and enemies with her magic rod. This concept sounds a bit silly, but as soon as I started to play the game, it became second nature.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for September! For next month I’ll be deep into Zelda and Metaphor for sure. Oh, and there’ll be also the new Shadow the Hedgehog game. Well, another busy month ahead. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Ooo wee, September, am I right? During this month I was able to finish the games I was playing last month and also to have a glimpse into October and the new games that come with it. September 2024 was also the month where I finally jumped into the next generation of consoles, or is it current generation, since it’s already almost four years old? Anyway, I got an Xbox Series X, which also had some impact on the games I played.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Persona</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Persona" /><published>2024-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona">&lt;p&gt;If you follow this blog for a while, you know that I’m a huge Persona fan. After playing the series’ most known installments, it was time for me to dive into the unknown; more precisely to the games before Persona 3. As I explained in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-3-reload&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload review&lt;/a&gt;, that game (not the version that I played, but the original one) introduced a formula that blends social simulation with the dungeon crawling typical of JRPGs, popularizing this series like never before. It happens that Persona 1 and 2 lack the focus on social elements, leaning more towards dungeon crawling, much like Shin Megami Tensei, the series that Persona is a spin-off of.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I provided myself with all the context necessary to approach the series’ first game. I even opted to play the improved 2009 PSP version over the original PS1 game from 1996, to avoid any potential headache with outdated mechanics. Even then, it was hard for me to have a good time with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-some-foundations&quot;&gt;Setting some foundations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first Persona game is a very different game from the most recent ones, I was pleasantly surprised to see here already some elements that defined the series. Starting with the very concept of Personas, spiritual creatures that give exceptional powers to their wielders. The Velvet Room, the place where those Personas are created and managed, also exists since the beginning, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VUCmZaG6tU0&quot;&gt;the same host and musical theme&lt;/a&gt;. Even the story and theming touches the same points as its successors, focused around a ragtag group of teenagers dwelling between alternate realities. Unfortunately, the delivery of all those elements is very subpar, particularly the main narrative. Don’t get me wrong, there are interesting aspects in it, but all of them were explored in much more interesting ways in the subsequent games.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my opinion, the biggest flaw of this game is the lack of depth of its characters, which is usually one of the things I seek the most in a Persona game. All of them except one (who is the center of the main narrative) are incredibly unidimensional, with all their interactions being based on their only personality trait. There were a few characters that I didn’t interact with, since there is an alternative story path that I didn’t play, but judging by the sample of my playthrough, I don’t imagine them to be much better.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NDjWo2wYaaE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The opening act of the game introduces us to the concept of Personas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;too-many-corridors&quot;&gt;Too many corridors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dungeon exploration in Persona is done in a first-person grid-based system, in the same style as some JRPGs before it such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/phantasy-star&quot;&gt;Phantasy Star&lt;/a&gt;. While they have some charm, the dungeons’ repetitive environments get old really fast. The case is aggravated with the biggest and more confusing dungeons. While navigating them, my entire focus was on the mini-map, since the endless samey corridors were a nightmare for orientation. The PSP version added the option for running, but even that didn’t solve the problem, only made it last less. For the cherry on top, we have good ol’ random encounters every god-damned five seconds! At least the turn-based combats aren’t that bad.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
During combat, we can either attack with weapon or gun (never stops being funny, and disturbing, seeing random teenagers wielding shotguns and snipers), use a Persona ability, or simply talk with the enemies. By choosing the non-violent option, we can convince them to leave, affect their status, or give us some item, if we choose the right dialog options. It’s by this method that we obtain spell cards, probably the most important item of this game. By fusing two spell cards, we can create powerful Personas, with new abilities. Why Atlus opted for such a complex system for one of the core mechanics is beyond me, but it seems they learned the lesson as they streamlined this process in the sequels.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The importance of having the right Persona for the right job cannot be understated and the final boss of the game, in the route I played, is the hardest reminder of that. No, literally. The difficulty spike is so immense that without Personas buffing considerably the characters’ stats and powers, it’s straight up impossible to defeat it. With them, it’s just brutally difficult. It’s a shame, because it left a terrible taste on an otherwise &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ouS_3wLpbbw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Designed as an authentic maze, Kama Palace is by far the most confusing dungeon in the entire game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two completely different story paths&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of life features introduced in the PSP version&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defined many core concepts of the Persona series&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soundtrack with a few great songs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persona management is overly complex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Little character development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very repetitive dungeons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly difficult final boss
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okay&quot;&gt;Okay&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✧✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persona is a game hard to recommend in the current day. It has the right ideas and intentions, but unfortunately, all of them are either underdeveloped or overly complex. On the bright side, it gave origin to one of the best JRPG series of all time.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">If you follow this blog for a while, you know that I’m a huge Persona fan. After playing the series’ most known installments, it was time for me to dive into the unknown; more precisely to the games before Persona 3. As I explained in my Persona 3 Reload review, that game (not the version that I played, but the original one) introduced a formula that blends social simulation with the dungeon crawling typical of JRPGs, popularizing this series like never before. It happens that Persona 1 and 2 lack the focus on social elements, leaning more towards dungeon crawling, much like Shin Megami Tensei, the series that Persona is a spin-off of. I provided myself with all the context necessary to approach the series’ first game. I even opted to play the improved 2009 PSP version over the original PS1 game from 1996, to avoid any potential headache with outdated mechanics. Even then, it was hard for me to have a good time with it. Setting some foundations</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope" /><published>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017, early in the Nintendo Switch lifecycle, a weirdly unconventional game developed by Ubisoft was released to rave reviews, to the surprise of everyone. There were a few reasons for a certain level of skepticism: Firstly, it promised to combine the Mario universe with the annoying Rabbids (who stole the Ubisoft mascot position from the vastly superior Rayman). Secondly, it was a turn-based strategy game, a totally new genre for the Italian plumber and his entourage. &lt;strong&gt;Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle&lt;/strong&gt;, as it was named, was a success in terms of critic and public acceptance. The fact of it being a great game might have contributed to that. It was without surprise that the development of a sequel was greenlit, that would eventually be released in 2022 by the name of &lt;strong&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-galaxy&quot;&gt;Into the Galaxy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the more grounded setup of Kingdom Battle, Sparks of Hope took its inspiration from the sensational Super Mario Galaxy. During our adventure, where we must defeat some evil entity that wants to destroy the universe or something like that, we travel across multiple planets with completely distinct biomes. Unfortunately, the space setting had less influence on the game than I would like, as we pass the entire time on the planets themselves. The space motif is mostly present in the battlefields’ background, but merely for cosmetic reasons, as it doesn’t affect the gameplay in any way. The story also doesn’t contribute to this setting in any particular way; actually, it doesn’t contribute to the game at all. It tries to be somewhat deep in certain aspects, like exploring the current problems each planet is facing, but it doesn’t scratch the surface for the most part. Maybe an overly simplistic narrative, as the mainline Mario games usually do, would work better here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On a bright side, each planet has a large overworld full of puzzles and secrets begging to be solved. This concept was already explored in the first game, but it was vastly expanded here. Unfortunately, the exploration is hindered by an overwhelming amount of loadings, even to access the most basic things like the planet map or the party selection screen. I know this is a very minimal issue, all things considered, but the impact it has on the gameplay can’t be neglected.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fiC-yLkx5p8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ From all the explorable planets in this game, Terra Flora was my favourite.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sparkling-battlefield&quot;&gt;Sparkling battlefield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of gameplay, this is where Sparks of Hope shines. The planet exploration already mentioned is a nice treat, but the true gameplay depth comes in the battlefields. Choosing a team of three characters of our choice, we must overcome a designated goal, be it defeat all enemies, reach a certain area or simply survive for a determined number of turns. Pretty standard goals for a turn-based strategy game. The interesting part comes when we actually have to move our characters. Unlike a typical grid-based movement, here we can move within a certain radius, defined by the respective character’s movement stat. When combined with the team jump mechanic (where a character can have a movement boost by jumping on a teammate) it allows for an unprecedented level of freedom within this game genre.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Taking care of the enemies is, without surprise, a challenge in itself. Many of them have different elemental weaknesses that must be exploited in order to succeed. To equip our team with elemental powers, we have Sparks - star-shaped floating creatures that provide special abilities to our characters. Think of Final Fantasy VII’s Materia; the concept is very similar. Before each battle, it’s imperative to analyze the field and understand what sparks we will need to overcome the challenge. I must confess it was a bit tedious to do that process before &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; battle, but without it, some of them would be borderline impossible to win.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pm-VoO_0P-o&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ An example of a battle in Sparks of Hope.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dynamic and engaging combat mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nice level of party customization with interchangable sparks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overworlds are fun to explore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly dull story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too… many… loading… screens
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good&quot;&gt;Good&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope is a game that shines in its combat, but falls short in its story and technical limitations. I definitely recommend it for fans of turn-based strategy games, but for everyone else, maybe any other Mario game would be more appealing.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Back in 2017, early in the Nintendo Switch lifecycle, a weirdly unconventional game developed by Ubisoft was released to rave reviews, to the surprise of everyone. There were a few reasons for a certain level of skepticism: Firstly, it promised to combine the Mario universe with the annoying Rabbids (who stole the Ubisoft mascot position from the vastly superior Rayman). Secondly, it was a turn-based strategy game, a totally new genre for the Italian plumber and his entourage. Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle, as it was named, was a success in terms of critic and public acceptance. The fact of it being a great game might have contributed to that. It was without surprise that the development of a sequel was greenlit, that would eventually be released in 2022 by the name of Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope. Into the Galaxy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – August 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – August 2024" /><published>2024-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24">&lt;p&gt;In a month where my biggest achievement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24&quot;&gt;going to Gamescom&lt;/a&gt;, playing games ironically have fallen a few steps in my priorities list. I finished a total of zero games in August, but was able to advance significantly in the ones I was already playing in July.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said last month, my expectations were very high, and I’m happy to report that they are being corresponded. In a gameplay perspective, it’s much more balanced and forgiving than the previous two. Being set mostly in wild environments instead of more closed areas gives much more freedom to sneak through the enemies. The story is also very gripping, specially considering this game marks the beginning of the Metal Gear timeline. Can’t wait to see what else the game has to offer.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing this first Persona is being… interesting. I’m not hating it, but I’m not loving it either. The story is confusing, the characters have little to no development, the dungeons are very inconsistent and the random encounter battles are tiresome. We can see here some ideas that would later be evolved and refined into something much better in later titles, but on its own, the first Persona is rough and outdated. I’ll finish it anyway, since I’m already way too invested on it, but I hope it gets better towards the end. Fingers crossed.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Wipeout Omega Collection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit sad to think that Wipeout Omega Collection, from 2017, which is already a remaster of Wipeout HD Fury and Wipeout 2048 from PS3 and PS Vita respectively, is to this day the last release in this historical franchise. Luckily it’s a phenomenal game (or should I say games?), running in buttery smooth 60fps and 4k visuals on a PS4 Pro, and PS5 by extension.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Valkyria Chronicles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tactical RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have yet much time to explore Valkyria Chronicles, but from the first few missions I had opportunity to play, I know for sure this is a game I’ll absolutely love. Not only it is a turn-based tactical game with a military theme, but it also plays a fictional anime-like rendition of World War II’s european theatre. It’s a bit weird, I assume, but not using the real countries names and geography it’s probably for the best. I also want to mention the absolutely epic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MP9rJdxmuQU&quot;&gt;main theme&lt;/a&gt; of the game, that sets perfectly the mood for what’s to come.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for August, see you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">In a month where my biggest achievement was going to Gamescom, playing games ironically have fallen a few steps in my priorities list. I finished a total of zero games in August, but was able to advance significantly in the ones I was already playing in July.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty" /><published>2024-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2">&lt;p&gt;After a whole life wondering what was so special about the Metal Gear series, for many people to consider it one of the best in videogame history, I decided to finally give it a chance at the beginning of this year. I started back in February with the first Metal Gear Solid (which I loved but didn’t have enough time to write a review of it) and then jumped immediately to its sequel. After watching its 12 minute long opening cutscene, I had to give it a break.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That break ended up lasting a few months, enough time to get over my Metal Gear induced hangover. You see, these are relatively short games, but insanely dense in terms of narrative and gameplay mechanics. While impressive from a technical standpoint (for a 2001 game), Metal Gear Solid 2 simply wasn’t clicking for me in the same way as the first. I had to force my way through, hoping for a silver lining along the way. What I ended up finding was way more rewarding and mind-blowing than I ever expected.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;claustrophobic-freedom&quot;&gt;Claustrophobic freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening chapter of Metal Gear Solid 2 is very reminiscent of the first game. We play as the very same Solid Snake in an environment somewhat similar to Shadow Moses, with a control scheme and gameplay structure very reminiscent of the previous adventure. However, everything feels more snappy than before. Snake’s moves are more fluid, there are many more ways to mess with the enemies’ minds and sneak through them, and the game itself looks and runs much better. All thanks to the power of the then brand new PlayStation 2. Instead of scaling up the scenarios, Hideo Kojima and his team chose to keep them tight, but much more crammed with details and small interactions. There were many instances where I opted to mess up my playthrough just to see the outcome of a certain action, like placing a trap for an enemy to fall on, even knowing that it would trigger an alarm. My only issue with all this freedom, is that it comes with a more complex control scheme. Getting used to it isn’t something trivial, but eventually it’s possible to get more comfortable with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
By the end of that first chapter the game already introduced all its core mechanics, that are mostly the same as its predecessor, but vastly improved. We are then put in the shoes of a rookie named Raiden. The mission is to rescue the US president from Big Shell, a facility in the middle of the Hudson river where he’s being held hostage by some terrorists. It’s from this moment on that Metal Gear Solid 2 transforms into a metanarrative, but that realization only comes near the end of it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ao-JO5jVGGA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The presence of the iconic Solid Snake is limited to the opening chapter... or is it?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-game-that-plays-you&quot;&gt;A game that plays you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a metanarrative wasn’t something new in the series by this point. The first Metal Gear Solid already had a few memorable fourth wall breaking moments, like the codec frequency printed in the game back cover, or Psycho Mantis &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t0oHnGM_iQw&amp;amp;t=88&quot;&gt;reading the player’s mind by commenting on the memory card game saves&lt;/a&gt;, but this second game pushes this concept way further. The more we play it and progress in its convoluted story, the more questions and inconsistencies we find regarding our mission objective(s) and the people surrounding Raiden.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The codec radio is without question the most quintessential narrative device of this game, probably even the entire series. It’s mostly through it that we communicate with the supporting characters and get vital information to progress in our mission. What would happen if that information wasn’t real? What would happen if the people we talk with weren’t real? Heck, what would happen if our own reality wasn’t real? That’s the scenario that Raiden, and we by extension, are confronted with at a certain point. Distinguishing what’s real from what’s a fabrication is a fascinating challenge that transcends the game itself. When the credits rolled I just sat silently, still figuring out what I just witnessed. I’ve just been played by this game, and I loved it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ul8j9I90ueM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ This is the point where the simulation started to implode, exposing the game's metanarrative.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uncanny attention to detail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great degree of freedom to approach most situations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game’s insane plot, focused around AI and misinformation, is more relevant nowadays than ever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convoluted control scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Constant switch between third-person and first-person views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not much environment variety
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty is simultaneously rooted in its origins and way ahead of its time. It’s simply one of those kinds of games that words alone can’t quite describe. The only way to understand it is to play it and fall for its ingenious metaphorical traps.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">After a whole life wondering what was so special about the Metal Gear series, for many people to consider it one of the best in videogame history, I decided to finally give it a chance at the beginning of this year. I started back in February with the first Metal Gear Solid (which I loved but didn’t have enough time to write a review of it) and then jumped immediately to its sequel. After watching its 12 minute long opening cutscene, I had to give it a break. That break ended up lasting a few months, enough time to get over my Metal Gear induced hangover. You see, these are relatively short games, but insanely dense in terms of narrative and gameplay mechanics. While impressive from a technical standpoint (for a 2001 game), Metal Gear Solid 2 simply wasn’t clicking for me in the same way as the first. I had to force my way through, hoping for a silver lining along the way. What I ended up finding was way more rewarding and mind-blowing than I ever expected. Claustrophobic freedom</summary></entry></feed>