<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://joaomarques.website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-30T10:34:27+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml</id><title type="html">João Marques | Abxy</title><subtitle>UX/UI Designer &amp; Frontend developer. Author of the gaming blog ABXY.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom" /><published>2024-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-echoes-of-wisdom">&lt;p&gt;It’s not very common in the long-running Zelda series for a game to be announced and released almost out of the blue, yet that’s exactly what happened with &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;. Only one short year after the monumental and highly anticipated &lt;em&gt;Tears of the Kingdom&lt;/em&gt;, Nintendo decided to announce this game, for the surprise of everyone - at least from my understanding. From the get-go, it was clear this would be a simpler game than its predecessor, marking a return to the series’ 2D gameplay style. However, that didn’t mean it was more of the same - quite the opposite, in fact. After all, it was the official debut of the titular princess as a protagonist - considering Nintendo refuses to acknowledge the existence of the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M52zKfu-cHk&quot;&gt;Philips CD-i games&lt;/a&gt; that also had Zelda as the playable character. From my experience, it was a meritorious debut, but with some glaring issues on its execution.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-power-of-wisdom&quot;&gt;The power of Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the lore of the series, princess Zelda is the triforce of Wisdom’s bearer and this game made sure to honour that. Unlike Link, Zelda isn’t equipped with a sword and shield, but with a magical rod. With it, we can create copies of various objects found in the world, known as &lt;strong&gt;Echoes&lt;/strong&gt;, and use them to overcome challenges, whether reaching specific locations or defeating enemies. For the former, we can use echoes of boxes, trees, trampolines, beds, and even blocks of water. For combat, we can “fight fire with fire” by creating echoes of the enemies themselves. Obviously is not that simple, with some of them requiring a bit more creativity to defeat, but there’s some satisfaction in doing it purely by brain power and not brute force. This is by far the biggest change in paradigm present in Echoes of Wisdom, with the difficulty coming more in form of mental puzzles and less in mechanical skill. And of course, having Zelda save Link - rather than the other way around - marks another change for the series status-quo.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Apart from the main character skillset, everything else is quite familiar to someone who played a Zelda game before. The most interesting aspect of it in my opinion is the blend of concepts between the traditional 2D games of the series and the open world ones (Breath of the Wild, Tears of the Kingdom), bringing elements from those such as a mission log, quick travel portals spread across Hyrule, unlinear progress (although much more toned down) and even cooking recipes.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/01onjjAUnOQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ A quick overview of Zelda's abilities in Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;echoes-of-issues&quot;&gt;Echoes of issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all the elements this game takes from its predecessors, there is one that’s much more evident than anything else. Back in 2019, Nintendo released a remake of the Game Boy classic &lt;em&gt;Link’s Awakening&lt;/em&gt;, in a completely new art style that resembled a diorama made with plastic pieces, looking almost like a Playmobil set. While initially strange, this aesthetic proved to work well once we acually the game. For &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt;, they decided to reuse the exact same style, but this time I found myself less impressed. Though charming, this style has creative limitations that lend a somewhat cheap aspect to the game - something difficult to explain in objective terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can explain objectively however is the terrible framerate the game has most of the time. This was already a problem in the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Link’s Awakening&lt;/em&gt;, that was also developed by the team behind this one, but here it gets even worse. By default it targets 60fps, but it can only reach them consistently in indoor environments, such as dungeons. While navigating through Hyrule, it rarely hits that target, sometimes going down to 20fps or even less. Sure, the Nintendo Switch is by today’s standards a very limited machine, but many games released for it proved that when well optimized, they can look and perform exceptionally well. &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/em&gt; should have been one of those cases, but unfortunately it isn’t.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zelda as a protagonist for a change!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Echoes mechanic is quite fun to play with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It borrows the best of the open-world 3D titles structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awful framerate drops while exploring the overworld&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toy-like aesthetic gets a bit old by the end of the game
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom is a worthwhile entry in the iconic series, successfully blending old and new elements. However, its technical issues and over-reliance on a limiting art style prevent it from reaching the heights of some of its predecessors.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">It’s not very common in the long-running Zelda series for a game to be announced and released almost out of the blue, yet that’s exactly what happened with Echoes of Wisdom. Only one short year after the monumental and highly anticipated Tears of the Kingdom, Nintendo decided to announce this game, for the surprise of everyone - at least from my understanding. From the get-go, it was clear this would be a simpler game than its predecessor, marking a return to the series’ 2D gameplay style. However, that didn’t mean it was more of the same - quite the opposite, in fact. After all, it was the official debut of the titular princess as a protagonist - considering Nintendo refuses to acknowledge the existence of the infamous Philips CD-i games that also had Zelda as the playable character. From my experience, it was a meritorious debut, but with some glaring issues on its execution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – September 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – September 2024" /><published>2024-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-sep-24">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V-_crlOw0HA&quot;&gt;Ooo wee&lt;/a&gt;, September, am I right? During this month I was able to finish the games I was playing last month and also to have a glimpse into October and the new games that come with it. September 2024 was also the month where I finally jumped into the next generation of consoles, or is it &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; generation, since it’s already almost four years old? Anyway, I got an Xbox Series X, which also had some impact on the games I played.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a game! It’s all I have to say now that I finished it. Expect a full review of it soon. I still have no idea of what I want to say about it, but I’ll get there eventually.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of reviews, I’m also done with Persona, however my opinion about this one isn’t as positive. You can already read my review &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Lego City Undercover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was something that I had for many years in my purgatory of unfinished games. I don’t even know why I abandoned it in the first place, as it isn’t a very long game to begin with, except if you decide to collect everything. Since I have better ways to waste my time, I decided to focus mostly on the main story. Overall it was a fun game, but nothing to write home about.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Grand Theft Auto: Stories from Liberty City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Xbox 360
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated in the intro paragraph, I just got an Xbox Series X. But as typical of this generation, I got the system but no games for it. However, this was nothing but a big brain plan from my side to test the backwards compatibility with Xbox 360 games, starting with GTA Stories from Liberty City, which is a standalone compilation of the two GTA IV expansions. I already finished the first one, The Lost and the Damned, but I still have the second one to play. In terms of gameplay, well, it’s more GTA, but with different protagonists. The true highlight here is the 60fps boost from playing it on the Series X. &lt;em&gt;Chef’s kiss.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio (Prologue Demo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Xbox Series X
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to have a glimpse of what will become of my gaming life until the end of this year, at least, by starting my journey in the highly anticipated Metaphor: ReFantazio. This is one of those demos that let you carry the save data to the full game, once it’s out by October 11th. So, if you are into RPGs and have a PC, PS4, PS5 or Xbox Series, please try this. It’s all I ask. It costs you nothing, except time. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Echoes of Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right at the tail end of the month, a wild new Zelda game appears! This time around we actually play as Zelda, who can replicate an innumerable amount of objects and enemies with her magic rod. This concept sounds a bit silly, but as soon as I started to play the game, it became second nature.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for September! For next month I’ll be deep into Zelda and Metaphor for sure. Oh, and there’ll be also the new Shadow the Hedgehog game. Well, another busy month ahead. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Ooo wee, September, am I right? During this month I was able to finish the games I was playing last month and also to have a glimpse into October and the new games that come with it. September 2024 was also the month where I finally jumped into the next generation of consoles, or is it current generation, since it’s already almost four years old? Anyway, I got an Xbox Series X, which also had some impact on the games I played.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Persona</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Persona" /><published>2024-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona">&lt;p&gt;If you follow this blog for a while, you know that I’m a huge Persona fan. After playing the series’ most known installments, it was time for me to dive into the unknown; more precisely to the games before Persona 3. As I explained in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-3-reload&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload review&lt;/a&gt;, that game (not the version that I played, but the original one) introduced a formula that blends social simulation with the dungeon crawling typical of JRPGs, popularizing this series like never before. It happens that Persona 1 and 2 lack the focus on social elements, leaning more towards dungeon crawling, much like Shin Megami Tensei, the series that Persona is a spin-off of.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I provided myself with all the context necessary to approach the series’ first game. I even opted to play the improved 2009 PSP version over the original PS1 game from 1996, to avoid any potential headache with outdated mechanics. Even then, it was hard for me to have a good time with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-some-foundations&quot;&gt;Setting some foundations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first Persona game is a very different game from the most recent ones, I was pleasantly surprised to see here already some elements that defined the series. Starting with the very concept of Personas, spiritual creatures that give exceptional powers to their wielders. The Velvet Room, the place where those Personas are created and managed, also exists since the beginning, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VUCmZaG6tU0&quot;&gt;the same host and musical theme&lt;/a&gt;. Even the story and theming touches the same points as its successors, focused around a ragtag group of teenagers dwelling between alternate realities. Unfortunately, the delivery of all those elements is very subpar, particularly the main narrative. Don’t get me wrong, there are interesting aspects in it, but all of them were explored in much more interesting ways in the subsequent games.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my opinion, the biggest flaw of this game is the lack of depth of its characters, which is usually one of the things I seek the most in a Persona game. All of them except one (who is the center of the main narrative) are incredibly unidimensional, with all their interactions being based on their only personality trait. There were a few characters that I didn’t interact with, since there is an alternative story path that I didn’t play, but judging by the sample of my playthrough, I don’t imagine them to be much better.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NDjWo2wYaaE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The opening act of the game introduces us to the concept of Personas.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;too-many-corridors&quot;&gt;Too many corridors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dungeon exploration in Persona is done in a first-person grid-based system, in the same style as some JRPGs before it such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/phantasy-star&quot;&gt;Phantasy Star&lt;/a&gt;. While they have some charm, the dungeons’ repetitive environments get old really fast. The case is aggravated with the biggest and more confusing dungeons. While navigating them, my entire focus was on the mini-map, since the endless samey corridors were a nightmare for orientation. The PSP version added the option for running, but even that didn’t solve the problem, only made it last less. For the cherry on top, we have good ol’ random encounters every god-damned five seconds! At least the turn-based combats aren’t that bad.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
During combat, we can either attack with weapon or gun (never stops being funny, and disturbing, seeing random teenagers wielding shotguns and snipers), use a Persona ability, or simply talk with the enemies. By choosing the non-violent option, we can convince them to leave, affect their status, or give us some item, if we choose the right dialog options. It’s by this method that we obtain spell cards, probably the most important item of this game. By fusing two spell cards, we can create powerful Personas, with new abilities. Why Atlus opted for such a complex system for one of the core mechanics is beyond me, but it seems they learned the lesson as they streamlined this process in the sequels.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The importance of having the right Persona for the right job cannot be understated and the final boss of the game, in the route I played, is the hardest reminder of that. No, literally. The difficulty spike is so immense that without Personas buffing considerably the characters’ stats and powers, it’s straight up impossible to defeat it. With them, it’s just brutally difficult. It’s a shame, because it left a terrible taste on an otherwise &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ouS_3wLpbbw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Designed as an authentic maze, Kama Palace is by far the most confusing dungeon in the entire game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two completely different story paths&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality of life features introduced in the PSP version&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defined many core concepts of the Persona series&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soundtrack with a few great songs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Persona management is overly complex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Little character development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very repetitive dungeons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly difficult final boss
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okay&quot;&gt;Okay&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✧✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persona is a game hard to recommend in the current day. It has the right ideas and intentions, but unfortunately, all of them are either underdeveloped or overly complex. On the bright side, it gave origin to one of the best JRPG series of all time.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">If you follow this blog for a while, you know that I’m a huge Persona fan. After playing the series’ most known installments, it was time for me to dive into the unknown; more precisely to the games before Persona 3. As I explained in my Persona 3 Reload review, that game (not the version that I played, but the original one) introduced a formula that blends social simulation with the dungeon crawling typical of JRPGs, popularizing this series like never before. It happens that Persona 1 and 2 lack the focus on social elements, leaning more towards dungeon crawling, much like Shin Megami Tensei, the series that Persona is a spin-off of. I provided myself with all the context necessary to approach the series’ first game. I even opted to play the improved 2009 PSP version over the original PS1 game from 1996, to avoid any potential headache with outdated mechanics. Even then, it was hard for me to have a good time with it. Setting some foundations</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope" /><published>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mario-rabbids-sparks-of-hope">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017, early in the Nintendo Switch lifecycle, a weirdly unconventional game developed by Ubisoft was released to rave reviews, to the surprise of everyone. There were a few reasons for a certain level of skepticism: Firstly, it promised to combine the Mario universe with the annoying Rabbids (who stole the Ubisoft mascot position from the vastly superior Rayman). Secondly, it was a turn-based strategy game, a totally new genre for the Italian plumber and his entourage. &lt;strong&gt;Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle&lt;/strong&gt;, as it was named, was a success in terms of critic and public acceptance. The fact of it being a great game might have contributed to that. It was without surprise that the development of a sequel was greenlit, that would eventually be released in 2022 by the name of &lt;strong&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-galaxy&quot;&gt;Into the Galaxy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the more grounded setup of Kingdom Battle, Sparks of Hope took its inspiration from the sensational Super Mario Galaxy. During our adventure, where we must defeat some evil entity that wants to destroy the universe or something like that, we travel across multiple planets with completely distinct biomes. Unfortunately, the space setting had less influence on the game than I would like, as we pass the entire time on the planets themselves. The space motif is mostly present in the battlefields’ background, but merely for cosmetic reasons, as it doesn’t affect the gameplay in any way. The story also doesn’t contribute to this setting in any particular way; actually, it doesn’t contribute to the game at all. It tries to be somewhat deep in certain aspects, like exploring the current problems each planet is facing, but it doesn’t scratch the surface for the most part. Maybe an overly simplistic narrative, as the mainline Mario games usually do, would work better here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On a bright side, each planet has a large overworld full of puzzles and secrets begging to be solved. This concept was already explored in the first game, but it was vastly expanded here. Unfortunately, the exploration is hindered by an overwhelming amount of loadings, even to access the most basic things like the planet map or the party selection screen. I know this is a very minimal issue, all things considered, but the impact it has on the gameplay can’t be neglected.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fiC-yLkx5p8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ From all the explorable planets in this game, Terra Flora was my favourite.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sparkling-battlefield&quot;&gt;Sparkling battlefield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of gameplay, this is where Sparks of Hope shines. The planet exploration already mentioned is a nice treat, but the true gameplay depth comes in the battlefields. Choosing a team of three characters of our choice, we must overcome a designated goal, be it defeat all enemies, reach a certain area or simply survive for a determined number of turns. Pretty standard goals for a turn-based strategy game. The interesting part comes when we actually have to move our characters. Unlike a typical grid-based movement, here we can move within a certain radius, defined by the respective character’s movement stat. When combined with the team jump mechanic (where a character can have a movement boost by jumping on a teammate) it allows for an unprecedented level of freedom within this game genre.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Taking care of the enemies is, without surprise, a challenge in itself. Many of them have different elemental weaknesses that must be exploited in order to succeed. To equip our team with elemental powers, we have Sparks - star-shaped floating creatures that provide special abilities to our characters. Think of Final Fantasy VII’s Materia; the concept is very similar. Before each battle, it’s imperative to analyze the field and understand what sparks we will need to overcome the challenge. I must confess it was a bit tedious to do that process before &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; battle, but without it, some of them would be borderline impossible to win.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pm-VoO_0P-o&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ An example of a battle in Sparks of Hope.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dynamic and engaging combat mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nice level of party customization with interchangable sparks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overworlds are fun to explore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly dull story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too… many… loading… screens
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good&quot;&gt;Good&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope is a game that shines in its combat, but falls short in its story and technical limitations. I definitely recommend it for fans of turn-based strategy games, but for everyone else, maybe any other Mario game would be more appealing.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Back in 2017, early in the Nintendo Switch lifecycle, a weirdly unconventional game developed by Ubisoft was released to rave reviews, to the surprise of everyone. There were a few reasons for a certain level of skepticism: Firstly, it promised to combine the Mario universe with the annoying Rabbids (who stole the Ubisoft mascot position from the vastly superior Rayman). Secondly, it was a turn-based strategy game, a totally new genre for the Italian plumber and his entourage. Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle, as it was named, was a success in terms of critic and public acceptance. The fact of it being a great game might have contributed to that. It was without surprise that the development of a sequel was greenlit, that would eventually be released in 2022 by the name of Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope. Into the Galaxy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – August 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – August 2024" /><published>2024-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-aug-24">&lt;p&gt;In a month where my biggest achievement was &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24&quot;&gt;going to Gamescom&lt;/a&gt;, playing games ironically have fallen a few steps in my priorities list. I finished a total of zero games in August, but was able to advance significantly in the ones I was already playing in July.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said last month, my expectations were very high, and I’m happy to report that they are being corresponded. In a gameplay perspective, it’s much more balanced and forgiving than the previous two. Being set mostly in wild environments instead of more closed areas gives much more freedom to sneak through the enemies. The story is also very gripping, specially considering this game marks the beginning of the Metal Gear timeline. Can’t wait to see what else the game has to offer.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing this first Persona is being… interesting. I’m not hating it, but I’m not loving it either. The story is confusing, the characters have little to no development, the dungeons are very inconsistent and the random encounter battles are tiresome. We can see here some ideas that would later be evolved and refined into something much better in later titles, but on its own, the first Persona is rough and outdated. I’ll finish it anyway, since I’m already way too invested on it, but I hope it gets better towards the end. Fingers crossed.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Wipeout Omega Collection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit sad to think that Wipeout Omega Collection, from 2017, which is already a remaster of Wipeout HD Fury and Wipeout 2048 from PS3 and PS Vita respectively, is to this day the last release in this historical franchise. Luckily it’s a phenomenal game (or should I say games?), running in buttery smooth 60fps and 4k visuals on a PS4 Pro, and PS5 by extension.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Valkyria Chronicles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tactical RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have yet much time to explore Valkyria Chronicles, but from the first few missions I had opportunity to play, I know for sure this is a game I’ll absolutely love. Not only it is a turn-based tactical game with a military theme, but it also plays a fictional anime-like rendition of World War II’s european theatre. It’s a bit weird, I assume, but not using the real countries names and geography it’s probably for the best. I also want to mention the absolutely epic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MP9rJdxmuQU&quot;&gt;main theme&lt;/a&gt; of the game, that sets perfectly the mood for what’s to come.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for August, see you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">In a month where my biggest achievement was going to Gamescom, playing games ironically have fallen a few steps in my priorities list. I finished a total of zero games in August, but was able to advance significantly in the ones I was already playing in July.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty" /><published>2024-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/metal-gear-solid-2">&lt;p&gt;After a whole life wondering what was so special about the Metal Gear series, for many people to consider it one of the best in videogame history, I decided to finally give it a chance at the beginning of this year. I started back in February with the first Metal Gear Solid (which I loved but didn’t have enough time to write a review of it) and then jumped immediately to its sequel. After watching its 12 minute long opening cutscene, I had to give it a break.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That break ended up lasting a few months, enough time to get over my Metal Gear induced hangover. You see, these are relatively short games, but insanely dense in terms of narrative and gameplay mechanics. While impressive from a technical standpoint (for a 2001 game), Metal Gear Solid 2 simply wasn’t clicking for me in the same way as the first. I had to force my way through, hoping for a silver lining along the way. What I ended up finding was way more rewarding and mind-blowing than I ever expected.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;claustrophobic-freedom&quot;&gt;Claustrophobic freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening chapter of Metal Gear Solid 2 is very reminiscent of the first game. We play as the very same Solid Snake in an environment somewhat similar to Shadow Moses, with a control scheme and gameplay structure very reminiscent of the previous adventure. However, everything feels more snappy than before. Snake’s moves are more fluid, there are many more ways to mess with the enemies’ minds and sneak through them, and the game itself looks and runs much better. All thanks to the power of the then brand new PlayStation 2. Instead of scaling up the scenarios, Hideo Kojima and his team chose to keep them tight, but much more crammed with details and small interactions. There were many instances where I opted to mess up my playthrough just to see the outcome of a certain action, like placing a trap for an enemy to fall on, even knowing that it would trigger an alarm. My only issue with all this freedom, is that it comes with a more complex control scheme. Getting used to it isn’t something trivial, but eventually it’s possible to get more comfortable with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
By the end of that first chapter the game already introduced all its core mechanics, that are mostly the same as its predecessor, but vastly improved. We are then put in the shoes of a rookie named Raiden. The mission is to rescue the US president from Big Shell, a facility in the middle of the Hudson river where he’s being held hostage by some terrorists. It’s from this moment on that Metal Gear Solid 2 transforms into a metanarrative, but that realization only comes near the end of it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ao-JO5jVGGA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The presence of the iconic Solid Snake is limited to the opening chapter... or is it?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-game-that-plays-you&quot;&gt;A game that plays you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a metanarrative wasn’t something new in the series by this point. The first Metal Gear Solid already had a few memorable fourth wall breaking moments, like the codec frequency printed in the game back cover, or Psycho Mantis &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t0oHnGM_iQw&amp;amp;t=88&quot;&gt;reading the player’s mind by commenting on the memory card game saves&lt;/a&gt;, but this second game pushes this concept way further. The more we play it and progress in its convoluted story, the more questions and inconsistencies we find regarding our mission objective(s) and the people surrounding Raiden.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The codec radio is without question the most quintessential narrative device of this game, probably even the entire series. It’s mostly through it that we communicate with the supporting characters and get vital information to progress in our mission. What would happen if that information wasn’t real? What would happen if the people we talk with weren’t real? Heck, what would happen if our own reality wasn’t real? That’s the scenario that Raiden, and we by extension, are confronted with at a certain point. Distinguishing what’s real from what’s a fabrication is a fascinating challenge that transcends the game itself. When the credits rolled I just sat silently, still figuring out what I just witnessed. I’ve just been played by this game, and I loved it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ul8j9I90ueM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ This is the point where the simulation started to implode, exposing the game's metanarrative.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uncanny attention to detail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great degree of freedom to approach most situations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game’s insane plot, focused around AI and misinformation, is more relevant nowadays than ever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convoluted control scheme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Constant switch between third-person and first-person views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not much environment variety
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty is simultaneously rooted in its origins and way ahead of its time. It’s simply one of those kinds of games that words alone can’t quite describe. The only way to understand it is to play it and fall for its ingenious metaphorical traps.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">After a whole life wondering what was so special about the Metal Gear series, for many people to consider it one of the best in videogame history, I decided to finally give it a chance at the beginning of this year. I started back in February with the first Metal Gear Solid (which I loved but didn’t have enough time to write a review of it) and then jumped immediately to its sequel. After watching its 12 minute long opening cutscene, I had to give it a break. That break ended up lasting a few months, enough time to get over my Metal Gear induced hangover. You see, these are relatively short games, but insanely dense in terms of narrative and gameplay mechanics. While impressive from a technical standpoint (for a 2001 game), Metal Gear Solid 2 simply wasn’t clicking for me in the same way as the first. I had to force my way through, hoping for a silver lining along the way. What I ended up finding was way more rewarding and mind-blowing than I ever expected. Claustrophobic freedom</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A day at Gamescom 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A day at Gamescom 2024" /><published>2024-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24">&lt;p&gt;Since I started to follow with more attention the videogame industry, I had this somewhat farfetched dream of attending an E3, which was for around 20 years the pinnacle of the medium. That dream never came to life since the days of E3 are now long gone. While &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/the-game-awards-2023&quot;&gt;The Game Awards&lt;/a&gt; absorbed some of the space left by it for the big and surprising game reveals, it was Gamescom who assumed the role of the biggest gaming conference in the world, growing considerably year by year in terms of attendance and relevance to the industry.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For me that was perfect, since a trip from Portugal to Germany, where the Gamescom is hosted, was way shorter and cheaper than to the United States. The dream was back on in a more attainable form - a win-win situation. With that in mind, I decided that this would be the year where I would attend Gamescom for the first time. I’m here now to tell you how it went.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-logistics&quot;&gt;The logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to an event of this magnitude required some preparation. From the accomodation to the experience while visiting it, many aspects had to be considered to take the most out of the day. This were my main considerations:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cologne, the city in the western part of Germany where all this happens, is a very expensive city. Flight directly to there and stay at the city can become extremely costly. I went for the most logical and affordable solution by staying at the neighbour city of Bonn, 20 minutes away by train. Luckily the event ticket came with a free transport pass for the region during the day of attendance, covering the commute expenses.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When entering the venue of Gamescom, one thing became abundantly clear: all food and drinks in there were also ridiculously expensive. I came prepared for that though. After a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Gamescom/comments/wvm828/can_i_take_food_with_me/&quot;&gt;quick search on Reddit&lt;/a&gt; I found out that consumables from outside were allowed, as long as they weren’t alcoholic or contained in glass. I was able to save some money and time as well, as I took the chance to eat during the queues to try some game demos.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was difficult to visit the entire venue in just one day. Not only it was massive in terms of area, but moving from hall to hall was a challenge on itself due to the massive crowds. I did a plan beforehand in order to prioritise what I really wanted to see and experience, but outside of that I simply didn’t have enough time to explore more what else Gamescom had to offer. In retrospective, two days would be the ideal timeframe to a more complete insight on the whole event.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-event&quot;&gt;The event&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gamescom had a lot of things to offer for a single day, to a point of being almost overwhelming. There were merchandise and artist alleys, cosplay contests, retro gaming areas, game tournaments, meet and greets, talks with game creators and many more. However, the main draw of the event was without doubt what they called of “Entertainment area”, where the companies present there put their best suits and presented their upcoming games in gigantic, colorful and captivating booths. I didn’t have opportunity to visit all them, but it was still possible to get some insights from an overall perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was an evident huge investment from asian companies besides Japan, most noticably the south korean Krafton, that was there mainly to promote their new social simulation game &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H6x864OOErk&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;InZOI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by flexing its powerful character creation tool. Hoyoverse from China also had a strong representation, promoting their hallmark games &lt;strong&gt;Genshin Impact&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Honkai: Star Rail&lt;/strong&gt;, beside their recently released &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-b_37whBVvA&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zenless Zone Zero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by offering enormous gift bags that turned their visitors into mobile outdors. Really clever, I must admit.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Household names like Ubisoft or Capcom also had a noticable presence there. The first was promoting &lt;strong&gt;Assassin’s Creed Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Star Wars Outlaws&lt;/strong&gt; while the latter put their money almost entirely on &lt;strong&gt;Monster Hunter Wilds&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually, the promotion for that particular game was so heavy that there were outdoors everywhere inviting people to their booth, even outside the boundaries of the venue, being spread around the digital advertisement panels of the city itself. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the big three console manufacturers, the only one who was there in a substancial form was Microsoft, showcasing &lt;strong&gt;Avowed&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Indiana Jones and The Great Circle&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Starfield Shattered Space&lt;/strong&gt;, to name a few. Sony was nowhere to be seen and Nintendo presence was limited to the Indie hall, supporting a few developers to showcase their titles for the Switch. Sony’s absense seems logical as they don’t have any upcoming flagship title, but Nintendo actually have a new Zelda about to be released, it seemed odd for them to not take the chance to promote it. I assume they are saving all their PR efforts to the reveal of their next system.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside the entertainment area, there were also a lot of interesting things to explore on the indie and retro gaming areas. On the indie one, there were simply too many games to try out, it was impossible to catch everything. I was able to briefly try two titles, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1830430/Grimoire_Groves/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grimoire Groves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1594060/Victory_Heat_Rally/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victory Heat Rally&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but both seemed to be still in a rough state to be honest. On the retro gaming area, there were a few booths of projects and entities dedicated to the subject, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/retrogamer_mag&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retro Gaming Magazine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, selling some of their editions (sadly only in german), and the Sega Saturn focused podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/6Uj3gD5KMQ4r4dJOjsknRF&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHIRO!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whose booth was obviously composed by several Saturns ready to be played. Unfortuately I didn’t spend as much time as I would like in this areas, but I will pay more attention to them if I ever return to the Gamescom in a future edition.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-demos&quot;&gt;The demos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s better than see new games? Playing them. I had the opportunity to watch exclusive gameplay of two titles from Bethesda and try out in first hand two other from Sega/Atlus. Here are my impressions from each one of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starfield Shattered Space:&lt;/strong&gt; This is an expansion that promises to deliver in areas where the base game was severly critizised for, particularly the environmental design, that will be composed by a handful of carefully crafted planets instead of a multitude of randomly generated ones, and the story. In visual terms, every footage they’ve shown looked way more eye catchy than everything the game offered before.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indiana Jones and The Great Circle:&lt;/strong&gt; A brand new game focused on the famous movie franchise where we impersonate a digital recreation of a young Harrison Ford, from a first person perspective. I have some reservations regarding that first person view, as it doesn’t look ideal for platforming. On the other hand, it’s the best choice for shooting and puzzle solving. I wonder how they will integrate seamlessly all this mechanics in the final product.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio:&lt;/strong&gt; This was by far the game I was most anticipating to play at Gamescom. Being from Atlus, it carries a lot of heritage from their previous games, starting by its development team, lead by the director of Persona 3, 4 and 5. Metaphor however is set in a medieval fantasy universe, contrasting with the contemporary setting of Persona. During the 15 minutes demo, I was able to experience a bit of the dungeon exploration and combat, that introduces a action oriented style, combined with the traditional turn-based one. From my limited experience, it works perfectly and it will make grinding much more fun and effortless. In the audio-visual department I have nothing but praise. In my opinion few companies make better game user interfaces than Atlus and Metaphor is here to prove it once again.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vgtv1orwhmU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ In the Metaphor: ReFantazio demo it was possible to explore a dungeon and even fight a boss.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sonic x Shadow Generations:&lt;/strong&gt; The last game I tried out during my time at Gamescom. Sonic Generations is essentially a remaster of the 2011 original for modern platforms, but what makes it interesting even for me, having played it back in the day, is the all new Shadow Generations. The model seems to be similar to Super Mario 3D World + Bowser’s Fury, essentially a compilation of two separated, yet related games. The demo available allowed me to experience two levels of each and my lasting impression of the new Shadow levels was really positive. They look great and play great, what more can I ask?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6lw7EAV-by4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The new Shadow levels are for sure the most interesting part of this new Sonic x Shadow Generations.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, going to the Gamescom was a fulfilling experience, even if a bit tiresome and overwhelming at points. I’m not sure if I’ll return next year, but I know (and I hope) this won’t be my last time here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lastly, I also participated on the latest episode of The Games Tome podcast, where I talked more in depth about everything I mentioned here (in 🇵🇹).
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B0MnYMpNpT8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ My participation at The Games Tome podcast, in an episode dedicated to this edition of the Gamescom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">Since I started to follow with more attention the videogame industry, I had this somewhat farfetched dream of attending an E3, which was for around 20 years the pinnacle of the medium. That dream never came to life since the days of E3 are now long gone. While The Game Awards absorbed some of the space left by it for the big and surprising game reveals, it was Gamescom who assumed the role of the biggest gaming conference in the world, growing considerably year by year in terms of attendance and relevance to the industry. For me that was perfect, since a trip from Portugal to Germany, where the Gamescom is hosted, was way shorter and cheaper than to the United States. The dream was back on in a more attainable form - a win-win situation. With that in mind, I decided that this would be the year where I would attend Gamescom for the first time. I’m here now to tell you how it went. The logistics</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – July 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – July 2024" /><published>2024-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24">&lt;p&gt;Here we are, August. As each month goes by, I have less ideas on what to write in this introduction paragraph. Let’s focus on what really matters here, the games:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I predicted on my last &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Played this month&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I got fully invested on Metal Gear Solid 2 and its completely bonkers plot. If the first MGS played a bit with fourth wall breaks and meta concepts, this one was all about them. This is the kind of game that let you thinking for hours about what you just witnessed after the credits roll. I’ll leave it like this for now, as I will save the details for the upcoming review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn-based strategy / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finished this month the second and possibly last game in the Mario + Rabbids series, as Davide Soliani, the director of both games, &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/DavideSoliani/status/1816050633343938597&quot;&gt;announced his departure from Ubisoft&lt;/a&gt;. It was kind of poetic to finish the game just a couple days before this announcement, as it was also my end of cycle with this series. As for Sparks of Hope itself, I’ll save my opinions for an eventual review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, more Metal Gear. For this one my expectations are unreasonably high, as it’s generally considered the peak of the series. For now, it’s still to early for me to have any sort of opinion, but next month I’ll probably have something to say about it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Ridge Racer 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My side project of this month was the restoration of a PSP. I had Ridge Racer 2 as the default game to test the system as I was fixing it. Without even noticing, I ended up playing (and winning) a couple of Grand Prix in it. It’s such a shame this series is pretty much dead nowadays, because there is no recent racing game that comes even close to capture its iconic style.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I went to such lengths to restore a PSP was precisely to continue my Persona journey. Sony’s first portable gaming system was blessed with not one but four Persona games during its time! I decided to start by the beginning, with the very first game (whose PSP version is a port of the PS1 original). Despite my short experience with it, I can already tell that this one is a very different beast from the others that I already played. One thing it has in common with those is its absolute &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nuKpIDf4U_o&amp;amp;list=PLX4JWB4HZSn9uFPQ2zTEbl5l72JamF3wO&quot;&gt;banger of soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;. Seriously, it’s hard to think of another series that is consistently spectacular on this aspect.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for July! For next month, I’ll be at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gamescom.global/en&quot;&gt;Gamescom&lt;/a&gt; (and Germany by extension) for the first time! I’ll do an article about my experience for sure. See ya!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Here we are, August. As each month goes by, I have less ideas on what to write in this introduction paragraph. Let’s focus on what really matters here, the games:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mother 3</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mother 3" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3">&lt;p&gt;Mother is arguably one of the most fascinating series from Nintendo’s long and iconic catalogue. When I say this, I’m not only referring to the games themselves but how they came to life. It was born out of the mind of Shigesato Itoi, a multi-talented Japanese celebrity who wanted to create an RPG based on a contemporary setting, unlike anything else that existed until that point, in the late 1980s. After some reluctance, he was able to convince Nintendo to work on his game. Mother, as it was named by Itoi himself, was released in Japan in 1989, being a success of sales and critics. However, it was its sequel that solidified the series’ cult status.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Released five long years later, due to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/2019/07/23/how-satoru-iwata-saved-earthbound-from-development-hell&quot;&gt;complex development cycle salvaged by the then Nintendo’s future president Satoru Iwata&lt;/a&gt;, Mother 2 was also positively received by Japanese audiences. Unfortunately, the same couldn’t be said about its international release, renamed as EarthBound. By 1995 standards, the game was perceived as outdated due to its simplistic and somewhat childish pixel-art style, resulting in mixed reviews and really poor sales outside its origin country. However, not many years later, with the advent of the internet and emulation, as well as a cameo in the Super Smash Bros. series, EarthBound gained a second life. People started to properly appreciate it outside the biased conventions of the media outlets at the time, to the point that it is nowadays considered one of the very best games ever made.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This leads us to Mother 3, which had an even more troubled development. It was initially conceived as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6pcd9VnnXSQ&quot;&gt;Nintendo 64 title with a 3D engine&lt;/a&gt;, but the scale and complexity of the project caused multiple delays, until it was officially canceled in 2000. But all hope wasn’t lost, because a few years later the development was rebooted for the Gameboy Advance, with visuals more in line with its predecessor, being finally released in 2006… exclusively in Japan.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Luckily for those who can’t read Japanese, a group of dedicated fans created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://mother3.fobby.net/&quot;&gt;English translation&lt;/a&gt;. It was precisely thanks to this translation that I was able to play this incredible game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;family-matters&quot;&gt;Family matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother 3 is focused around a young boy named Lucas and his family, who live in a small rural town named Tazmily, where everyone is friendly and respectful to each other. Everything is good until the day the village is invaded by some mysterious and hostile military forces. Amidst all the chaos caused by them, something terrible happens to Hinawa and Claus, the mother and twin brother of Lucas respectively. The story then jumps to a period three years after that tragic event. By then, the depth of the writing, scenario, and character development becomes evident. We still find most of the people we met during the epilogue, but their lives changed drastically since then, as did the village itself. Tazmily became much more industrialized and its people more individualistic. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tazmily is just the tip of the iceberg on everything Mother 3 has to offer in terms of narrative. There are a lot of smaller stories within the village itself, but me writing about all of them not only would make this review unbearably huge, as it wouldn’t do them justice. Actually, there is a particular aspect in this game that is quite unusual for a story-driven RPG - During most of it, we don’t have even the slightest clue about our end goal, we are just following a succession of random events, but damn, the journey is so gripping. Most of the merit is on the brilliant writing for the small moments, being them happy, sad, or plain funny, especially when they come at the most unexpected times. How a simple game can convey such strong emotions is something that I can’t quite explain, but even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z8YaKuWLvGs&quot;&gt;Nintendo’s marketing team knew&lt;/a&gt; it was Mother 3’s &lt;em&gt;secret sauce&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7YnbMbI8aKE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The first chapter of Mother 3 ends in a tragic tone and with a lot of mysteries to uncover.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-world-of-quirkiness&quot;&gt;A world of quirkiness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this review has been focused exclusively on storytelling so far, Mother 3 has more to offer than that. In terms of gameplay, it’s a traditional RPG, but with a few twists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The party:&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of a consistent group of characters, our party changes constantly according to the story progress. We only get the “definitive” party by the penultimate chapter. That chapter is also by far the longest one, taking almost half of the game’s runtime.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The combat:&lt;/strong&gt; For the most part, it follows the traditional turn-based system, where each character can attack physically or psychically (the equivalent of a magic power), defend, or use items. The first twist comes in the way the HP counter works. When an enemy attacks, instead of dealing all the damage at once to a character, their HP starts to roll down gradually, like a car odometer, but in reverse. By acting fast it’s possible to avoid what would be otherwise a certain death, by healing before the counter reaches zero. If we choose to defend, the counter also rolls slower than usual. The other interesting twist in the game’s combat is the timed attack mechanic. By timing the attacks to the beat of the background music, our characters can deal extra hits (and do a jamming session as a bonus). Mastering this technique is fundamental to beat certain bosses, as some of them can be &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The enemies:&lt;/strong&gt; While not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; enemies are super weird, many of them are. A perfect example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UE3BUoWGmEw&quot;&gt;Negative Man&lt;/a&gt;, a rectangular creature that seems to be incredibly depressed and implores us to kill it. Although, what’s even more captivating than the characters themselves, is how they are presented - as a static image over a psychedelic background animation. All their interactions are conveyed through visual effects and micro-interactions in the HUD. Conceptually it may look like a terrible idea, but the execution was inexplicably flawless.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The items:&lt;/strong&gt; There are no swords or guns in Mother 3. Most items found in the game are mundane objects. Yo-Yos, sticks, and even rolled pamphlets serve as weapons, for example. This gives an overall sense of groundedness to the game, even when it goes to places way far detached from reality.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All this beautiful weirdness is amplified by an equally beautiful and weird soundtrack, comprised of more than 200 unique songs! From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q3Xsy_Ual8o&quot;&gt;happy&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XU4AK4NZ2Q&quot;&gt;sad&lt;/a&gt; themes, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RK960EqwS1Q&quot;&gt;something in between&lt;/a&gt;, the musical variety present here is impressive.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3a_IuOffRYw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Mother 3 was re-released on the Nintendo Switch Online service exclusively in Japan, yet again.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I decided to play this game my expectations were already high, even so, it was able to surprise me in a positive way many times during my journey with it. I couldn’t ask for more. Mother 3 is brilliant in its uniqueness.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quirky sense of humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple and yet very emotional story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect the unexpected all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beautiful and expansive soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Superb fan translation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few unbalanced difficulty spikes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clunky item management
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpiece&quot;&gt;Masterpiece&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t describe Mother 3 in one sentence, there’s so much more to it than meets the eye. If your thing is story-driven games, just do a favor to yourself and play it. It’s all I can say.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Mother is arguably one of the most fascinating series from Nintendo’s long and iconic catalogue. When I say this, I’m not only referring to the games themselves but how they came to life. It was born out of the mind of Shigesato Itoi, a multi-talented Japanese celebrity who wanted to create an RPG based on a contemporary setting, unlike anything else that existed until that point, in the late 1980s. After some reluctance, he was able to convince Nintendo to work on his game. Mother, as it was named by Itoi himself, was released in Japan in 1989, being a success of sales and critics. However, it was its sequel that solidified the series’ cult status. Released five long years later, due to a complex development cycle salvaged by the then Nintendo’s future president Satoru Iwata, Mother 2 was also positively received by Japanese audiences. Unfortunately, the same couldn’t be said about its international release, renamed as EarthBound. By 1995 standards, the game was perceived as outdated due to its simplistic and somewhat childish pixel-art style, resulting in mixed reviews and really poor sales outside its origin country. However, not many years later, with the advent of the internet and emulation, as well as a cameo in the Super Smash Bros. series, EarthBound gained a second life. People started to properly appreciate it outside the biased conventions of the media outlets at the time, to the point that it is nowadays considered one of the very best games ever made. This leads us to Mother 3, which had an even more troubled development. It was initially conceived as a Nintendo 64 title with a 3D engine, but the scale and complexity of the project caused multiple delays, until it was officially canceled in 2000. But all hope wasn’t lost, because a few years later the development was rebooted for the Gameboy Advance, with visuals more in line with its predecessor, being finally released in 2006… exclusively in Japan. Luckily for those who can’t read Japanese, a group of dedicated fans created an English translation. It was precisely thanks to this translation that I was able to play this incredible game. Family matters</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – June 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – June 2024" /><published>2024-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24">&lt;p&gt;For the first time since January, I was able to publish at least two game reviews here at ABXY! To the ones who’ve read them, thank you. I hope you like the stuff I wrote, even if sometimes it’s nonsense gibberish. By the way, feel free to give feedback if you have any (I believe I have my X profile on the footer)! Anyway, this month was also prolific in terms of games finished, which means more reviews to write. It’s a never ending circle, what have I done…
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first game I finished this month. This is one I’ll never forget, for how funny and emotional it was. I’ll save the details for a full review, but you can count on a “Masterpiece” evaluation.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Sonic Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Sega Dreamcast
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the very same day, I also finished Sonic Adventure. You can already read &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-adventure&quot;&gt;my review&lt;/a&gt; of it!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Paper Mario: The Thousand-Year Door&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a game that I intended to play on its original GameCube version, but then I found the recently released Switch remaster at a good price and decided to go for it. I only played for a couple of hours, but it was enough to defeat the first boss. I will keep this one on hold until I finish the other games I have in progress.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn-based strategy / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this game last year as a birthday gift for myself, but it didn’t click for me as its predecessor (Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle) even after playing until almost half of its campaign. In an effort to finish games I had in progress, I decided to give it a second chance. I’m glad I did it, as I was able to ignore the things I didn’t like before and focus on the good ones, in particular the unique combat system that blends turn-based with real-time strategy.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;EA FC 24&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football simulation / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Euro time! Or it was, until Portugal and every underdog I was rooting for were eliminated. But before that, I was able to do a run with Ronaldo and company in EA FC 24 and lift the trophy. Case to say that in my simulation the captain was the best scorer of the tournament, which unfortunately proved to be a shocking departure from reality.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m back to the biggest Kojima’s fever dream! I needed some time away from the Metal Gear Solid series to properly assimilate the first game, but now I’m ready to embrace its sequel.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that’s all for June. During July I’ll probably be fully invested in Metal Gear and all its craziness. I’ll tell you how it went next month.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">For the first time since January, I was able to publish at least two game reviews here at ABXY! To the ones who’ve read them, thank you. I hope you like the stuff I wrote, even if sometimes it’s nonsense gibberish. By the way, feel free to give feedback if you have any (I believe I have my X profile on the footer)! Anyway, this month was also prolific in terms of games finished, which means more reviews to write. It’s a never ending circle, what have I done…</summary></entry></feed>