<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://joaomarques.website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-06T22:39:57+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml</id><title type="html">João Marques | Abxy</title><subtitle>UX/UI Designer &amp; Frontend developer. Author of the gaming blog ABXY.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Played this month – April 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – April 2024" /><published>2024-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, another month, another update. This time, as if two JRPGs weren’t enough, I decided to start (and luckily finish) one more. I even had to refrain myself from starting a fourth one. I’m clearly on my JPRG era, much like a teenager obsessed with My Chemical Romance, or whatever they listen these days. It will pass eventually, probably when I finish Persona 3 Reload.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are, once again. I’m starting to run out of things to say about this game, as it makes by now three months since I started playing it. I’m definitely near its final, but from my experience with this series, that’s equivalent to no less than 20 hours of gameplay. At least its story it’s &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; getting interesting.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another follow up from last month. I’m having a great time with it so far, with 10 hours clocked in by this point. The more I play it, the more I understand why it wasn’t released outside Japan. I have a feeling that current day Nintendo would never do a game like this. I will save the details for an eventual review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Phantasy Star&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Sega Master System
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had some fascination for Sega’s oldest RPG series, but never had interest in actually playing the games before. That finally changed when I got the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6hIwDZqiMD4&quot;&gt;Sega Ages&lt;/a&gt; version of this Master System classic. This version, released for the Nintendo Switch, had a ton of quality of life features that made possible finishing it much faster than the original one. It’s surely a product of its time (and that time is 1987), but in terms of story and world building it’s still very fresh. While every other RPG of this era was focused solely on medieval fantasies, Phantasy Star took its inspiration from science fiction instead.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Streets of Rage 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beat’em’up / Sega Mega Drive
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the objective of giving more use to my Mega Drive, and eventually play Phantasy Star II, III and IV with rom hacks in the original hardware, I got an Everdrive, a cartridge that reads games from an SD card. I decided to test it with one of the best games for the system, Streets of Rage 2. Smashing delinquents to the sound of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pXLpubTPO94&quot;&gt;Yuzo Koshiro’s techno soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; is pure dopamine. Without even noticing, I finished it in one try.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for April. For next month, I promise to bring fewer RPGs. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Hi everyone, another month, another update. This time, as if two JRPGs weren’t enough, I decided to start (and luckily finish) one more. I even had to refrain myself from starting a fourth one. I’m clearly on my JPRG era, much like a teenager obsessed with My Chemical Romance, or whatever they listen these days. It will pass eventually, probably when I finish Persona 3 Reload.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fallout (TV show)</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fallout (TV show)" /><published>2024-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show">&lt;p&gt;While I initially only envisioned reviewing video games in this space, I decided to make an exception for the Fallout TV show, that premiered recently on Amazon Prime Video. Since this show is set in the same universe as the games and is technically part of the story canon, a review here isn’t too out of place. I’m also taking the opportunity to talk about it while it’s still a hot topic. Keep in mind that even if this review isn’t spoiler heavy, I will mention some facts and events that you might want to discover by yourself, if you haven’t watched the TV show yet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-vault-life&quot;&gt;A vault life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fallout universe is set in an alternate reality where nuclear bombs were massively deployed soon after World War II, profoundly affecting human scientific and technological advancements, culture, and the planet’s ecosystem. This led to the origin of the “wasteland”, where survival is the primary concern.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Away from the dire reality of the wasteland, a few selected individuals live in underground vaults spread across the United States. It’s precisely in one of this vaults that this show starts. We are quickly introduced to one of the main characters, Lucy, and to the busy life inside the vault 33, as the main goal of the vault dwellers - to repopulate the surface once the radiation levels are dissipated from it. However, things went terribly wrong for the inhabitants of Vault 33 when they were invaded and massacred by wastelanders, who also abducted Lucy’s father, the vault overseer, in the process. Lucy then decides to leave the vault for the first time in her life to find her father, echoing Fallout 3’s prologue.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There were still a lot of questions to answer regarding what happened in vault 33. Thankfuly the show does a great job on exploring the motivations behind such tragedy, as the mystery involving two other interconnected vaults, 31 and 32, conducted by the few survivors. Although this subplot was one of the most interesting parts of the show, it unfortunately remained unresolved. Let’s hope it has a follow up in season 2.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/V-mugKDQDlg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The trailer unveils the three main characters: Lucy, Maximus and Cooper.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-wasteland-journey&quot;&gt;The wasteland journey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already on the wasteland, Lucy’s path crosses with Maximus, a member of Brotherhood of Steel, a military order with the goal of control humanity’s most advanced technologies. Always mistreated inside the order, Maximus was sent on a mission to support a soldier retrieving a particular piece of technology. Unsurprisingly, the mission deviated from the plan, but Maximus gained the upper hand by seizing control of the soldier’s armor. Then we get the classic arc of the underdog that once it reaches the top, becomes what he despised the most. While not deal breaking for me, I just didn’t found his story interesting at all, specially because his realization comes really sudently and by the end he’s already the same old good natured underdog, but simply more powerful.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The third main character, who also crosses with Lucy during her journey, is in my opinion the most interesting one. Formerly a Hollywood actor and propaganda man for Vault-Tec, the company responsible for the underground vaults, Cooper Howard has since become a ghoul due to the devastating effects of the nuclear bombs. In this universe, ghouls are essentially people who got too much exposure to radiation, giving them a decomposed appearance, but also a much prolonged life span. During the entire season, our point of view from Cooper is constantly shifting between the past, before the bombing, and the present. What led him to accept doing advertisement for Vault-tec, oblivious of their obscure interests, and what made him eventually become the sour and ruthless ghoul he is.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Creating an original narrative and new characters was a winning choice from the showrunners. It gives something new for everyone, either long time fans or newcomers to the complex Fallout universe. What makes this show trully special however, is how they were able to capture perfectly the games’ essence, consisting of a mixture of dry (and sometimes dark) humor, some spectacularly gory scenes and a retro-futuristic aesthetic heavily inspired by the post-war America from the 40’s and 50’s.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fallout lore was used to perfection to build a brand new story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The series typical dry humor and ocasional gore are present here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A great introduction for newcomers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot of callbacks to the games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maximus story arc was a bit too cliché for my taste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vault 31, 32 and 33 mystery didn’t have a proper resolution
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fallout, the TV show, joined the recent trend of great videogame adaptations, reviving the interest in a franchise that was dormant since the controversial release of Fallout 76. In case you have Amazon Prime, go watch it. In case you don’t, use a free trial. It’ll be worth, believe me.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">While I initially only envisioned reviewing video games in this space, I decided to make an exception for the Fallout TV show, that premiered recently on Amazon Prime Video. Since this show is set in the same universe as the games and is technically part of the story canon, a review here isn’t too out of place. I’m also taking the opportunity to talk about it while it’s still a hot topic. Keep in mind that even if this review isn’t spoiler heavy, I will mention some facts and events that you might want to discover by yourself, if you haven’t watched the TV show yet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – March 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-mar-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – March 2024" /><published>2024-04-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-mar-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-mar-24">&lt;p&gt;Can you believe March is already over? I can’t. For me at least it was a quite hectic month, reflected with the radio silence here in this last few weeks, since the release of the post celebrating the &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/7-years-nintendo-switch&quot;&gt;7 years of Nintendo Switch&lt;/a&gt;. But enough of excuses. For this catch up, I bring a respectable amount of games, all things considered, but most of my time was invested in two japanese RPGs with a number 3 on their title. Quite fitting for the third month of the year, don’t you think? Without further ado, here’s what I played in March:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS1
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally understand all the cult status behind Hideo Kojima and the Metal Gear franchise, now that I finished Metal Gear Solid. For a PS1 game from 1998 it has aged very gracefully, due to its voice acting, cinematography and gameplay. I will keep it short for now, as I will eventually do a review for this game. I have too many things to say about it, I just don’t know yet how to phrase them.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;em&gt;full-time job&lt;/em&gt; of this month. With 40 hours clocked in so far, I don’t know exactly how many I still have left in this expansive RPG, but I’m enjoying it so far. One thing I have to mention though, is the social links, which are essentially the friendships we can have in the game. Many of them suck, with the interactions with those characters ranging from painfully cringe to just boring. This was an aspect that was &lt;em&gt;vastly&lt;/em&gt; improved in Persona &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-4-golden&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still fresh from Metal Gear Solid, it was only logical that I would want to play its sequel. With that in mind I got a PS3, as it is to this day the only platform where the series can be played in its entirety. Regarding this second game, I only watched the 15 minute long intro cutscene and did not much else, but it got me intrigued.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Formula One Championship Edition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the start of the F1 season, I went to search for a good classic F1 game. I ended up finding this Formula One Championship Edition, a game developed by the creators of Wipeout that served as a launch title for the PS3, with an accurate representation of 2006 F1 season. Many aspects of this game held up quite well to this day, such as the graphics, gameplay… and the presence of Fernando Alonso, already world champion by the time this game was released.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few series have a stronger cult status as Mother. One of the major causes for it, beside its uniqueness, is the mystery behind its international localizations. During many years, Mother 2 was the only game of the series officially released outside Japan, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vGOEMCG2Ll4&quot;&gt;Earthbound&lt;/a&gt;. Mother 1 was released out of the blue for the Wii U Virtual Console in 2015, 26 years after the japanese version, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ttKkiEKqwuk&quot;&gt;Earthbound Beginnings&lt;/a&gt;. As for Mother 3, arguably the best of the bunch, it suffered the worst fate, never receiving an international release to this day. Luckily, a group of talented fans did what &lt;em&gt;Nintendon’t&lt;/em&gt; and created an incredible &lt;a href=&quot;https://mother3.fobby.net/&quot;&gt;english translation&lt;/a&gt;. It’s thanks to them that I’m now playing this game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Star Fox Command&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoot’em up / Nintendo DS
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing a video from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@GVG&quot;&gt;Good Vibes Gaming&lt;/a&gt; (a great Youtube channel that I totally recommend) about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l_d3H2bkZHM&quot;&gt;improving Nintendo DS games on the 3DS&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to try this Star Fox Command, as it was mentioned there. Unlike the other games in the series, this one combines the spaceship flying and shooting with some turn based tactics, which is totally my jam. So far it has been a pleasant surprise.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that’s all for March. For next month, I have no idea, but I’ll try to focus on what I already have in progress. I need some closure, and closure won’t come if I keep adding games to my backlog.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Can you believe March is already over? I can’t. For me at least it was a quite hectic month, reflected with the radio silence here in this last few weeks, since the release of the post celebrating the 7 years of Nintendo Switch. But enough of excuses. For this catch up, I bring a respectable amount of games, all things considered, but most of my time was invested in two japanese RPGs with a number 3 on their title. Quite fitting for the third month of the year, don’t you think? Without further ado, here’s what I played in March:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">7 years of Nintendo Switch</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/7-years-nintendo-switch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 years of Nintendo Switch" /><published>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/7-years-nintendo-switch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/7-years-nintendo-switch">&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to believe but 2017 was already 7 years ago. The world was different back then, as Nintendo itself. Nowadays it seems almost unthinkable, but the house of Mario was in serious trouble before the release of the hybrid system that revolutionised the gaming market and gave a whole new life to portable systems. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s look back at the inception of the Nintendo Switch, how it became so successful and what it still has left to give.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nintendos-ace-in-the-hole&quot;&gt;Nintendo’s ace in the hole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying that Nintendo had a few rough years before the release of the Switch is quite an understatement. After the staggering success of the Wii, the company decided to release its successor, the Wii U, in 2012. Although, its confusing proposition, baffling name and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4e3qaPg_keg&quot;&gt;terrible marketing&lt;/a&gt; caused it to flop hard. For “hardcore” gamers, it wasn’t powerful enough to deliver the third party games present on the other systems (which was already a problem with the original Wii), and the “casual” audience didn’t even understand that Wii U was actually a new system, neither needed one (as most of them only played Wii Sports anyway). Even the relative success of the Nintendo 3DS wasn’t enough to compensate for the huge financial losses caused by this misstep. As a consequence of that, the company’s president Satoru Iwata famously cut his salary in half to avoid layoffs, a move that made him be in good graces of many fans, alongside his charisma and genuine passion for gaming. Unsurprisingly, his death in 2015 was another hard blow in Nintendo’s already low spirits.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything was doom and gloom though, with the development of the next system being already underway. In that same year the first news about it surfaced, while the full reveal only happened one year later, in 2016. It was undoubtedly a smart move. Nintendo always had a strong grasp on the portable gaming market, so, an hybrid system like the Switch was the logical step in hindsight. Instead of supporting two systems simultaneously, like it happened before (the 3DS still coexisted with the Switch for a couple of years, but it was quickly phased out), they could combine all their efforts on a single platform. Of course there were still concerns about the system modest specs, as it could fall in the same pattern of not getting third party multi-platform games due the disparity with the other available systems. Luckily the Nintendo Switch was a success right out of the box when it launched, in March 3 2017, in due part to their &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; ace in the hole.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iS-1tDfLxRQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The Nintendo Switch was introduced to the world with this trailer, back in late 2016.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-all-about-the-games&quot;&gt;It’s all about the games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lineup of games available on launch day was nothing to write home about, but it didn’t matter. The highly anticipated The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild was the most compelling argument to get the Switch day one. The game was so successful that not only revolutionised the Zelda franchise, but the entire open-world genre. While it was also released simultaneously for the Wii U, it was more out of obligation its loyal user base, since it was developed with that system in mind to begin with.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Breath of the Wild was enough to keep the new Switch owners busy for a few weeks (if not months), but the first year of the console would see an influx of great exclusive releases, such as Splatoon 2, Mario Kart 8 Deluxe, Xenoblade Chronicles 2 and Super Mario Odyssey. By the end of 2017, it was clear that the Switch was here to stay. With a good user base and the novelty of playing on TV or on the go, third party developers interest grew substantially. The efforts put in ports like Skyrim, The Witcher 3, Doom or Dark Souls proved that there was market for this kind of re-releases. The graphical downgrade was a compromise many people were willing to accept, with the prospect of having the flexibility of playing this games on a portable form factor. The indie scene was (and still is) also a force to be reckoned with in the Switch library. Since those games usually aren’t as graphically demanding as high budget ones, they are released on Nintendo’s system without compromises, making the Switch the ideal place to play them.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my case, what made me jump to the Switch bandwagon was the release of Super Smash Bros. Ultimate, in late 2018. I was already a fan of the series, so, when Ultimate was announced with the promisse of including all the characters from the previous entries, I knew it was time to get a Switch. Sadly I had to wait a few months to play it, since the physical edition of the game was sold out everywhere during that holiday season. Instead I ended up picking Super Mario Odyssey as my first Switch game. Case to say that I had no regrets with that decision, because it was absolutely fantastic! It became instantly my favourite Mario game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/w3Gt42kVgCw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The game reveal that made me buy a Switch back in the day.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;something-called-animal-crossing&quot;&gt;Something called Animal Crossing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Switch concept was more than solidified to the gaming audience, it wasn’t until the release of Animal Crossing: New Horizons that the system had its breakout moment with the casual public. Animal Crossing was a life simulation series where the player could live a parallel life with cute anthropomorphic animals, following the real life time and calendar. After a few years of hiatus, the fans were eager for the series return. The concept of this new entry, titled New Horizons, was to move to a deserted island and developing it with cultivations, houses, infrastructures and more, while creating relationships with the few animals who choose to live there as well. The game looked great and promissed a ton of content, judging by the trailers revealed until then. The hype machine was building up for the game release in March of 2020. I don’t know if you remember by now, but there was &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; global trend that started to grow insanely that same month. Covid-19 forced many of us to obligatory lockdowns and many people started looking into forms of escapism to deal with the situation. What could be more enticing than living a nice life in a island far away from all the real world problems?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From that point onwards sales of the system and software skyrocketed and a new wave of games appeared trying to appeal to this new audience interested in farming simulators and “cozy” games. The Switch truly felt like a system for everyone.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ie4WZCLbtVs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Animal Crossing: New Horizons success is one of the best examples of right place, right time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fading-into-the-sunset&quot;&gt;Fading into the sunset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything good eventually comes to an end, as is the case with the Switch. While 2023 was still an incredible year in terms of new releases, (Super Mario Wonder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-tears-of-the-kingdom&quot;&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/pikmin-4&quot;&gt;Pikmin 4&lt;/a&gt;, to name a few), 2024 looks much more bleak in contrast. Most of the exclusive titles of this year are essentially remakes and remasters, some justifiable (Paper Mario: The Thousand Year Door), others not really (Mario vs Donkey Kong). Having the knowledge to make an educated guess, I say this is a clear sign that the main development efforts are being put somewhere else, very likely in a new system. This statement can age either like wine or milk, but I’m truly confident that this will be the last year of the Switch as the main Nintendo system, with the reveal of the next one not very far away.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s impossible to know for sure what’s going to happen next, but nobody can take from us the seven years of the tiny gaming tablet (yes, it has a touchscreen, even if few games used it) that served as home for some of the finest games ever made.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">It’s hard to believe but 2017 was already 7 years ago. The world was different back then, as Nintendo itself. Nowadays it seems almost unthinkable, but the house of Mario was in serious trouble before the release of the hybrid system that revolutionised the gaming market and gave a whole new life to portable systems. Let’s look back at the inception of the Nintendo Switch, how it became so successful and what it still has left to give.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – February 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-feb-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – February 2024" /><published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-feb-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-feb-24">&lt;p&gt;As I predicted &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jan-24&quot;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt;, this month was mostly about Persona, yet again. I’m fully aware that this blog is one step short of transforming into a Persona Fan Club, but that’s a risk I’m willing to take. Anyway, I still had time to play a few other things. Here’s what February looked like:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one was a given. As soon as the remake of the third Persona game was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QIIPXA2A6cM&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;, with new visuals and quality-of-life improvements brought from Persona 5, I knew it was a day one purchase for me. My time with this game so far has been great, with around 20 hours clocked in. I’m still relatively in the beginning of the story, as nothing really interesting happened yet, but the combat and character development are keeping me engaged so far.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;No More Heroes 2: Desperate Struggle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hack’n’slash / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a week away from home (and from Persona 3 Reload), as so I took the opportunity to bring the Switch with me and play a short game from my backlog, with No More Heroes 2 being the chosen one. You can already read &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/no-more-heroes-2&quot;&gt;my review of it&lt;/a&gt;, in case you didn’t yet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS1
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close the month, I decided to finally dive into Hideo Kojima’s best-known series. While in the beginning I struggled a bit to truly understand the game mechanics, now I’m completely hooked. It’s hard to believe this game is 25 years old, with the only evidence of that being the charming PS1 polygonal graphics.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that’s all for February. Not a lot of games, but the few ones were really worth my time. For next month, expect more Persona and more Metal Gear Solid. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">As I predicted last time, this month was mostly about Persona, yet again. I’m fully aware that this blog is one step short of transforming into a Persona Fan Club, but that’s a risk I’m willing to take. Anyway, I still had time to play a few other things. Here’s what February looked like:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No more heroes 2: Desperate Struggle</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/no-more-heroes-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No more heroes 2: Desperate Struggle" /><published>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/no-more-heroes-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/no-more-heroes-2">&lt;p&gt;There are few series with such a unique vibe as No More Heroes. Brainchild of the extravagant game designer Goichi Suda (AKA Suda51), No More Heroes is heavily characterized by a mix of over-the-top violence, a self-aware sense of humor, and a ton of references and homages to other games and movies. Imagine &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7wd5KEaOtm4&quot;&gt;Scott Pilgrim&lt;/a&gt;, but with much more blood and censurable language.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While not published by Nintendo, this series is somewhat associated with their systems, as the two first games were designed around the Wii, and the third one around the Nintendo Switch. It was precisely with the third installment that I discovered this series, as it was revealed during a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=91HU_mc9cts&quot;&gt;Nintendo Direct&lt;/a&gt;. I started my journey with No More Heroes with its first game though, to get some knowledge of the lore and characters. But after that, in a hurry to play the newest game, I decided to completely ignore the second one. I must admit I didn’t regret that decision, as I absolutely loved No More Heroes III, despite its flaws.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For a long time, I had no interest in playing No More Heroes 2, as I was almost sure I wouldn’t like it as much as its successor, but now, almost two years later, I finally decided to give it a chance. It turns out my assumption was right, but I still had a good time with it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ranking-up-by-revenge&quot;&gt;Ranking up by revenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first No More Heroes we play as Travis Touchdown, a professional assassin with a unique taste for wrestling and anime, that’s challanged by a girl to climb up to the first rank of the UAA (United Assassins Association) in order to have a chance with her. That’s it, that’s the premisse.
And how exactly does the process of ranking up works? With deadly one-on-one matches with each ranked assassin. After reaching the number one rank and ending up without the girl, as she decides to not honor her part of the deal, Travis decides to retire from the “business”. All is good until his best friend is killed by revenge for someone Travis killed before. Coincidently, the person who plots this assassination is now the new number one of the UAA ranking.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It is with this renewed motivation that Travis Touchdown decides to rank up once again, marking the start of No More Heroes 2. Unlike the first game, where he started ranked 11th, he’s now ranked at a distant 51st place. While initially it’s assumed that we would need to do 50 battles to get our desired revenge, we soon realize that the game defies our expectations by killing off more than half of those assassins off-screen during the course of the story at the most unexpected times. By the end of the game we end up actually fighting, and killing, 15 of those assassins.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speaking on combat, that’s the aspect that had the biggest improvement comparing with its predecessor. While in the first game the combat relied mostly on counter-attacks, making it a waiting game most of the times, this one gives more freedom to approach the enemies, be it by brute force, hit and run, or still by counter-attack.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Timu1cp9zh0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ One of the many ranking battles we face during the game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-more-side-jobs&quot;&gt;No more side jobs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of this series uniqueness lies in everything else we do beside fighting. Unfortunately that’s where in my opinion No More Heroes 2 fumbles the most. In the other games we are somewhat forced to do random jobs to have money to pay the ranked battles entry fees, with those jobs ranging from minor killing sprees to some mundane tasks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nEIkr5RceJQ&quot;&gt;lawn mowing or unclogging toilets&lt;/a&gt;. It’s ridiculous for sure, but that’s the point. It’s satirical.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are still side jobs in No More Heroes 2, but they are presented in an 8-bit style this time around. They are mildly fun, but mostly useless. Unlike on the other two games, here there are no entry fees for the ranked battles, as so, the money can only be used to buy new clothes, weapons and going to the gym (to upgrade life and attack power). But even considering the gym upgrades, which are in fact useful, there is no need to hustle for extra cash, as we can gather enough just by going through the ranked battles. Buying weapons isn’t necessary as well, especially when the best one is given to Travis during the course of the story. The game can be entirely played without even interacting with this extra content, as it doesn’t even have a freely explorable hub world, being replaced by a simple menu.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vsVFxY2S1o4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ All the side jobs plays like a NES game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All things considered, nothing in No More Heroes 2 is actually bad, but the decision to cut the open world exploration (that made its comeback on No More Heroes III) and the battle entry fees made a huge part of the game completely redundant. I still did every side job anyway, but they just felt like a mini-game compilation attached without rhyme or reason to a good hack’n’slash game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refined hack’n’slash mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nonsense story is backed by its unique sense of humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most ranked battles are epic and incredibly fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almost all side content is pretty much pointless&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of open world exploration
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good&quot;&gt;Good&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No More Heroes 2 is the definition of two steps forward one step back. While the main course is definitely an improvement from its predecessor, literally everything else is a letdown.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">There are few series with such a unique vibe as No More Heroes. Brainchild of the extravagant game designer Goichi Suda (AKA Suda51), No More Heroes is heavily characterized by a mix of over-the-top violence, a self-aware sense of humor, and a ton of references and homages to other games and movies. Imagine Scott Pilgrim, but with much more blood and censurable language. While not published by Nintendo, this series is somewhat associated with their systems, as the two first games were designed around the Wii, and the third one around the Nintendo Switch. It was precisely with the third installment that I discovered this series, as it was revealed during a Nintendo Direct. I started my journey with No More Heroes with its first game though, to get some knowledge of the lore and characters. But after that, in a hurry to play the newest game, I decided to completely ignore the second one. I must admit I didn’t regret that decision, as I absolutely loved No More Heroes III, despite its flaws. For a long time, I had no interest in playing No More Heroes 2, as I was almost sure I wouldn’t like it as much as its successor, but now, almost two years later, I finally decided to give it a chance. It turns out my assumption was right, but I still had a good time with it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pikmin 4</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/pikmin-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pikmin 4" /><published>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/pikmin-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/pikmin-4">&lt;p&gt;Since its inception, the Pikmin franchise has always been highly praised, and yet, very niche. Created in 2001 by the legendary game designer Shigeru Miyamoto (which you may know for the Mario or Zelda series, to name a few), it had since suffered two very long hiatus, to the point where some fans even thought it was dead. The first one between Pikmin 2 (2004) and Pikmin 3 (2013), and the last since last year, when Pikmin 4 finally came out. Nintendo however had already tested the interest for a new game before, with the relatively successful release of Pikmin 3 Deluxe for the Nintendo Switch, back in 2020. Luckily for me, I discovered this series in that same year, during the pandemic lockdown, so I didn’t have to endure the long droughts.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But what all this has to do with Pikmin 4? As it turns out, this new entry not only embrace the entire series legacy, as it reinvent and expand it significantly.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-canonical-reboot&quot;&gt;A canonical reboot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Pikmin 1, we control a tiny astronaut named Captain Olimar, who crashes on an alien planet that closely resembles Earth, (although it’s never disclosed that it’s actually our Earth). He has 30 days to collect all the missing parts of his spaceship, in order to get back home before he runs out of vital supplies. Luckily a few small creatures that grow like plants befriends with him and help him carry those missing parts and fight other not so friendly creatures, as long as Olimar helps to grow more their population. Those creatures are the titular Pikmin, and they exist in several varieties with distinct properties, such as resistance to fire, or ability to swim. The challenge is basically to command the Pikmins to overcome the challenges imposed to us, by alternating between the varieties best suited for specific tasks.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Pikmin 4, we also start with Captain Olimar and a similar premise, although, in this case the mission doesn’t end well, neither for him nor the rescue corps that received his distress signal. Although, there was one last rookie rescue officer available to help. It’s precisely that rookie, that can be customized to our image, that we control during the rest of the game. Our main goal is to rescue all this people lost on the planet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tqpbMLVa9EI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ A brief introduction to Pikmin 4's plot and main mechanics.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rescuing-the-rescuers&quot;&gt;Rescuing the rescuers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as we start our mission, we realise that there are much more castways needing rescue than anticipated, beside the rescue corps. Apparently many different people were already exploring this planet for very different reasons, but all of them ended in a similar way - either unconscious or infected by a condition that transformed them in some kind of pikmin themselves. In the later case, to rescue them, we need to defeat them in a “Dandori” battle, where the goal is to collect more treasures than the opponent in a confined space and a limited amount of time. But the rescue doesn’t end there. To cure their unique condition, we need to collect a nectar that’s only available during night. As so, beside the usual daily expeditions, where we start at the morning and leave by sunset, we have, for the first time in the series, night expeditions. During those, we only have access to a new type of glowing pikmins and our job is to protect the sources of the nectar from the enemies until sunrise, functioning like a tower defense game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These two new type of challenges, Dandori battles and night expeditions, bring a fresh spin to the gameplay loop of the series, that before that had its focus solely on collecting treasures. By the way, treasures are still here and continue to be a crucial part of the game, as they serve as fuel for our spaceship in order to explore more areas. Nonetheless, the biggest gameplay innovation Pikmin 4 brings is in the form of Oachi, a dog from the rescue corps that we can use in many different ways. Oachi can carry all the pikmins and ourselves to cross lakes or protect from enemies, carry treasures, break obstacles, fight enemies, and even control pikmins, enableing some degree of multitasking.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-love-letter-to-the-fans&quot;&gt;A love letter to the fans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a lot of new mechanics were introduced, the developers were clever enough to understand what elements worked the best in the previous entries and bring them back. The most obvious example of that are the caves, which were a core part of Pikmin 2. While on that game the caves were procedurally generated, creating a lot of unbalanced (and many times infuriating) level designs, in Pikmin 4 all caves are carefully designed, delivering a much more refined experience.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Besides the mechanics, the characters and travel logs also reveal a lot of references to the previous games events, some more obvious than others. After rescuing Captain Olimar, which is the main part mission and what will trigger the ending credits, we can play a new mode where we relive the events from his shipwrecking to the distress signal sending. For new players, this would be just more content to play, which is always nice, but for those who played every previous game to this point, becomes clear that it’s essentially the campaign of the very first Pikmin game, reinvented to fit the current narrative and environments. To have such thing as just a clever bonus content, put in perspective the enormous scope and attention to detail put in Pikmin 4.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ton of treasures to collect and castways to rescue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Dandori battles and night expeditions give a solid but fair challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best mechanics of the 3 previous games are present here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The perfect game for both rookies and veterans of the series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soundtrack is a bit forgettable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UI menus are more generic, comparing with the previous entries
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpiece&quot;&gt;Masterpiece&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pikmin 4 was successful in the arduous task of being accessible for new players, while rewarding the longtime fans with a compelling experience full of nods to the series previous entries.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Since its inception, the Pikmin franchise has always been highly praised, and yet, very niche. Created in 2001 by the legendary game designer Shigeru Miyamoto (which you may know for the Mario or Zelda series, to name a few), it had since suffered two very long hiatus, to the point where some fans even thought it was dead. The first one between Pikmin 2 (2004) and Pikmin 3 (2013), and the last since last year, when Pikmin 4 finally came out. Nintendo however had already tested the interest for a new game before, with the relatively successful release of Pikmin 3 Deluxe for the Nintendo Switch, back in 2020. Luckily for me, I discovered this series in that same year, during the pandemic lockdown, so I didn’t have to endure the long droughts. But what all this has to do with Pikmin 4? As it turns out, this new entry not only embrace the entire series legacy, as it reinvent and expand it significantly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – January 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jan-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – January 2024" /><published>2024-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jan-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jan-24">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the first “Played this month”. This will be, as the name suggests, a series where I give some brief personal opinion about the games I played during the month that just ended. In January I tried a few new games (new at least for me), but only two of them really got my full attention and dedication. Here’s what I played:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Final Fantasy VII Remake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of the Final Fantasy VII Remake trilogy was the first game I finished this year. It’s focused in Midgar, where the original game starts, giving to the city a gigantic facelift with detailed graphics, for the most part, and spectacular cutscenes, in classic Square Enix fashion, and introducing a new action focused combat system. Overall it was a great experience, but not without a few flaws, like some lackluster side quests, to give an example.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Pikmin 4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real-time strategy / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Pikmin fan, this was a game I knew I would have a great time with, even before starting to play it. After almost 40 hours of gameplay and 100% completion, it managed to not only match my high expectations but even surpass them. I will keep it short for now, as I will do a full review of Pikmin 4 soon.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Fire Emblem Echoes: Shadows of Valentia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tactical RPG / Nintendo 3DS
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My quest to find a Fire Emblem game that I like more than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rkux5h0PeXo&quot;&gt;Three Houses&lt;/a&gt; is yet prove to be fruitless. Echoes: Shadows of Valentia was the closest I got from that, but even so, I didn’t have the drive to keep playing it until the end. My save file was abandoned for almost an year, much like my Nintendo 3DS. I decided to do a quick battle, just to try to get back in the game, but I forgot completely the story so far and many of the characters. I may need to watch a recap before playing more.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Very Very Valet&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casual / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago in a company retreat I had, I tried a few casual multiplayer games whose names I can’t even remember, but one of them stood from the crowd to me. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=feyHL0GfcIo&quot;&gt;Very Very Valet&lt;/a&gt; combined the Overcooked-like co-op strategy with some crazy driving mechanics, in the same style as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R5x547gzU_g&quot;&gt;Micro Machines&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EA-430ZNqZg&quot;&gt;R.C. Pro-Am&lt;/a&gt;, to deliver an hilariously chaotic experience.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Shin Megami Tensei V&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After enjoying &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-4-golden&quot;&gt;Persona 4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt; so much, I decided to try the series that started it all, just to realize how brutally difficult it is, to the point that on my third regular battle, I was presented with the Game Over screen. SMT V is what can be described as a true “hardcore” experience. It didn’t convinced me in the same way as its more successful spinoff, as so, I will put this game on hold for now. The only thing I truly enjoyed during my brief time with it, was its soundtrack. Seriously, it seems like Atlus simply can’t make games without some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ohi99qWYngc&quot;&gt;bangers&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that’s all for January. For next month, one thing I know for sure, it will be all about the new Persona 3 Reload. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Welcome to the first “Played this month”. This will be, as the name suggests, a series where I give some brief personal opinion about the games I played during the month that just ended. In January I tried a few new games (new at least for me), but only two of them really got my full attention and dedication. Here’s what I played:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Persona 5 Royal</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Persona 5 Royal" /><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal">&lt;p&gt;This review is the last part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/my-2023-in-gaming&quot;&gt;My 2023 in Gaming&lt;/a&gt; retrospective, with Persona 5 Royal earning the distinction of my favorite game of last year.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In terms of video games, 2023 was the year of Persona for me. If you are following my retrospective series, you may have already come to that conclusion. But my obsession with the franchise started back in 2022 when I decided to finally give a chance to a game that so many people talked wonders about. The game in question? In case you didn’t read the title of this review, it’s Persona 5 Royal. To give you a bit of context, I never had much interest in JRPGs (Japanese role-playing games) before. My only experience worth noting with the genre was a couple of hours in Final Fantasy VII before I dropped it for whatever reason (I intend to replay it properly in the near future, though). But there was something about Persona 5 that always drew my attention. It was not the detailed anime-like aesthetic, nor the captivating gameplay. It was actually its sense of style, present in all clips and trailers I saw from it. The impulse to play Persona 5 once and for all came when ports of it were announced for Nintendo Switch, Xbox, and PC. The marketing surrounding them put the game again on my radar, and so, I snagged a cheap second-handed copy for the PS4, just to try it. To my surprise, I got immediately hooked.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tokyo-daylife&quot;&gt;Tokyo daylife&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persona 5, being a Persona game, follows for the most part the classic Persona formula. If you don’t know what any of this means, I vividly recommend you to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-4-golden&quot;&gt;my review of Persona 4 Golden&lt;/a&gt;, where I explain briefly how this unique franchise works. While the previous games opted for smaller or lesser-known settings around Japan, this one went for the iconic capital city, Tokyo. During the many hours of gameplay, you can explore many well-known locations, such as Shibuya crossing and its surroundings. While I can’t say how faithful the in-game recreations of these places are, since I’ve never been to Japan, I can tell there is a feeling of authenticity in them. One place in particular that I want to highlight is actually the humble neighborhood of Yongen-Jaya, where the game’s protagonist lives during its events.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/O6cOSc1SIy8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The night view of Shibuya crossing in Persona 5.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;into-the-metaverse&quot;&gt;Into the Metaverse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our protagonist, in classic Persona fashion, is a teenager who is forced to get away from his hometown and spend an entire year in a new city. This time around, the reason is probation imposed on him, due to a crime he was wrongly accused of. For some reason, a family friend who lives in Tokyo accepted to welcome him during that period, keeping him under a watchful eye. While still adapting to his new life by getting to know his classmates and teachers at his new school, he accidentally ends up in a parallel reality, known as the “Metaverse” (no, it’s not the one that you are thinking of). In this Metaverse, the protagonist finds distorted (and deeply disturbing) versions of people he met in the real world, including the one responsible for his crime accusation. Those versions consist of the personification of their twisted desires, and it’s our job, by incarnating this protagonist, to defeat them with our Persona abilities.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the many questionable people we meet during the game’s narrative is the school’s PE teacher and volleyball team coach, who abuses physically and sexually his trainees. In the Metaverse, he takes the form of a king, living in a castle guarded by tokenized versions of those same trainees. This castle is actually the first of many dungeons present in the game. As in the case I just mentioned, every dungeon is carefully designed around the person we must defeat, as are the real-world events surrounding it, making them a spectacular part of the full experience.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hb1gfNgOAwo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The first explorable dungeon we encounter in this game.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stylish-rebellion&quot;&gt;Stylish rebellion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the spectacularity of these dungeons, and the entire game, is severely amplified by its incredible art direction. Character and scenario designs aside, the real star of the show, in my opinion, is the user interface. Persona 5, like any RPG, relies a lot on many different menus for all kinds of actions, and every single one of them here has unique layouts and animations presented in a punk aesthetic, fitting the game’s theme of breaking society’s moral corruption. If that wasn’t enough, such visual galore is scored by one of the best soundtracks I ever had the pleasure to hear in a video game, composed in a jazzy style (in lack of a more technical term). Any words I write here won’t do justice to it, so the best I can do is to recommend you to listen to it for yourself.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border-radius:12px&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/4pJT0WKggr4xk149X8A6KC?utm_source=generator&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;152&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VqJnmphV9R8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ It's not often that I can say it's a joy to use a game menu.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Persona 5 is undeniably fantastic, it’s worth noticing its biggest issue: its longevity. Depending on the person, this can be either a problem or a benefit. It took me 132 hours to finish the game, and I still missed several things during my playtime. The case is ‘aggravated’ in its Royal version (the one I played), which expands significantly the length of the story. It’s a great bang for your buck for sure, but if you are someone like me, who likes to play several different games in many different styles, being stuck in a single one for months can be just a bit tiresome. Even so, on the day after I finally ended my lengthy journey with Persona 5 Royal, I was already missing it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unique and impactful art style&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazing, explorable dungeons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Story full of deep and morally dark themes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the best original soundtracks ever created for a game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It requires a significant time investment just to finish it
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpiece&quot;&gt;Masterpiece&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even considering it’s not a game for everyone, Persona 5 Royal is without a doubt one of the very best ever made. Its incredible sense of style and attention to detail brought many new fans to this fantastic series, with me being one of them.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">This review is the last part of My 2023 in Gaming retrospective, with Persona 5 Royal earning the distinction of my favorite game of last year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-tears-of-the-kingdom" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom" /><published>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-tears-of-the-kingdom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/zelda-tears-of-the-kingdom">&lt;p&gt;This review is part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/my-2023-in-gaming&quot;&gt;My 2023 in Gaming&lt;/a&gt; retrospective, with The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom being my second favourite game of last year.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Few games raise unreasonably high expectations upon release as a new Zelda. It isn’t by chance. More than 35 years of nothing but incredible games guaranteed such a reputation for the iconic Nintendo series. Most of those games’ style and lore work in isolation, being only connected by a loose &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q-25c8Rsobw&quot;&gt;timeline&lt;/a&gt;, but after the staggering success of Breath of the Wild, it wasn’t a huge surprise when the company announced back in 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Zr9eAtwcYlo?si=KLAEfvjHVjsW6qwZ&amp;amp;t=2466&quot;&gt;during one of its presentations&lt;/a&gt;, a direct sequel to it. Well, it was a surprise nonetheless, but it made total sense. The game had a long development cycle, and its fresh new gameplay formula still had a lot to give. The hope, for us fans, was that a direct sequel would take less time to develop, since they already had many core elements in place. Oh boy, how we were wrong. Four long years separated that reveal trailer from the actual release date. Was the wait worth it? In my view, it was, but not without a few minor hiccups.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;that-déjà-vu-feeling&quot;&gt;That déjà vu feeling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action of Tears of the Kingdom occurs at the exact same version of Hyrule (the kingdom present in some form in most Zelda games) as Breath of the Wild, which grants an unavoidable sense of familiarity to those who played that game. One of the most enjoyable aspects of the experience back then was to discover gradually all the interconnected regions of the kingdom, just to be surprised by their completely distinct biomes. Obviously, most of that is gone now that we are presented with the same challenge again. Although, many things changed in the land of Hyrule between both games. The lives of the Hylians we meet before had moved on, and many of them have new stories and challenges to unfold. Some even relocated to entirely new places. Not only that, but many regions now face particular climatic issues, changing dramatically the feeling and exploration of them. But the most evident change is without a doubt the mysterious appearance of countless islands in the sky. This is thrown to our face right from the beginning, since it’s on one of those islands where the game properly begins.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-sky-is-the-limit-literally&quot;&gt;The sky is the limit, literally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start our journey on a floating island that conveniently introduces us to all the new (and old) game mechanics. Think of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/wikis/the-legend-of-zelda-breath-of-the-wild/Great_Plateau&quot;&gt;Great Plateau&lt;/a&gt;, but in the sky. We have our shrines, and they work in the exact same way as before. We are gradually introduced to our new array of abilities and forced in some way to put them in use. After that, we are left to our own devices and invited to dive off the island into a pond on the distant surface. When arriving there, we are presented with several weird holes in the ground, some of them bigger than the pond where we just dived. By jumping into any of them, a whole new dark and unwelcoming underworld is revealed to us. That’s right! This Hyrule has two extra layers beside the already gigantic surface level, significantly increasing its scope. The game even plays with this verticality with some puzzles interconnecting all three layers, by starting in the highest point in the sky and ending in the darkest depths. And if you’re wondering, yes, it’s possible to skydive from an island straight down to the underworld, seamlessly.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The renovated world is only part of the reason why this game is impressive, though. What takes Tears of the Kingdom to the next level is what we can do in it. As I mentioned before, we are given four main abilities that change dramatically the way we interact with the environment: &lt;strong&gt;Ascend&lt;/strong&gt; lets us merge into most surfaces above us and rise on top of them. It’s very useful to escape caves or wells, but it can be used in more cases than that. &lt;strong&gt;Recall&lt;/strong&gt; allows us to revert the flow of time of any object. &lt;strong&gt;Fuse&lt;/strong&gt;, as the name suggests, lets us fuse a weapon or shield to another object, allowing us to improve their properties or even give them powerful, and sometimes funny, new perks. The star of the show, though, is &lt;strong&gt;Ultrahand&lt;/strong&gt;. With it, it’s possible to remotely manipulate and glue together as many objects as we want. By itself, it’s impressive, but when combined with the many ancient technological artifacts left around the world, such as rockets, wheels, fans, laser beams, and many more, they invite the player to engineer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m9_O94KqRAo&quot;&gt;the most useful, or absurd, creations&lt;/a&gt;. Such a powerful tool comes with the price of being a bit cumbersome to use because everything is done in real time. There is no separated creation mode. But after a few dozen hours, it’s possible to get the gist of it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a6qna-ZCbxA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The game's producer Eiji Aonuma, demonstrating the new abilities firsthand.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;demon-king-secret-stone&quot;&gt;Demon King? Secret stone?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time now to address what is, in my opinion, the elephant in the room in Tears of the Kingdom: its story. In short, it doesn’t work really well. Two things that were promised during the months before its release were that the game would feature the return of dungeons in a more “classic” style and would tell a more complex narrative. While the first promise was somewhat delivered (even considering a very underwhelming water dungeon), the second failed because of the game’s structure. You see, Breath of the Wild had a very simple plot, but it was brilliantly executed. You learned the full story by collecting small pieces of information without any specific order, but none of those pieces required much context to be understood.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With Tears of the Kingdom, they decided to use the exact same plot structure but with a more interconnected plotline. During most of the game, I was completely clueless about what was actually happening story-wise and how I would complete my main objective, which was to find Zelda. Oh yeah, I totally forgot to explain that part. So, long story short: Link and Zelda were exploring some underground ruins and suddenly they find a recurring villain of the series, Ganondorf, also known as the “Demon King,” in a decayed state, held by a mysterious glowing arm. Ganondorf awakes, throws Zelda into a dark pit, and almost kills Link. Then, Link awakens on the sky island I mentioned before, with that very same glowing arm in place of his own injured one. Confused? Me too. In the lack of a better expression, this plot is completely bonkers. The worst part, in my opinion, is what happens next. Link is told that some strange phenomena are happening at the same four main locations that were home to the four divine beasts from Breath of the Wild and that, for some reason, could be related to Zelda’s disappearance. After we clear each one of the region’s subplots, we are presented with a very similar cutscene each time, only differing in the people involved. Each and every time, the character in question says the exact same thing. By the fourth time I heard &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iU5q0dFeHVI&quot;&gt;“Demon King? Secret Stone?”&lt;/a&gt; my faith in this plot was practically gone.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/umwKE9paVwg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The events that trigger this rather confusing plot.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s so obvious that this story was built around the gameplay that it hurts. But you know what? I’m glad it was like that and not the other way around. Obviously, a balanced approach was the ideal scenario, but I understand it was an almost impossible task to build a concise story without sacrificing some of the freedom. Fun was clearly the priority with Tears of the Kingdom, and I wouldn’t have it any other way.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New abilites turned Hyrule into the best playground ever&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The scope and verticality of the game world is unprecedented&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ultrahand ability usage is a bit convoluted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The narrative is weakened by its non-linear presentation
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpiece&quot;&gt;Masterpiece&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom is a very difficult game to objectively analise. It does have clear issues, but only because it tries to reach highs that others don’t even dream to. Even so, I say without any reservations that it is one of the most engineous open-world sandbox experience ever made.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">This review is part of My 2023 in Gaming retrospective, with The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom being my second favourite game of last year.</summary></entry></feed>