<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://joaomarques.website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-10T00:48:53+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml</id><title type="html">João Marques | Abxy</title><subtitle>UX/UI Designer &amp; Front-end developer. Author of the gaming blog ABXY.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Winners and Losers of The Game Awards 2023</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/the-game-awards-2023" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Winners and Losers of The Game Awards 2023" /><published>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/the-game-awards-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/the-game-awards-2023">&lt;p&gt;Beside the usual festive season, the end of the year is now also marked by a more recent tradition, The Game Awards. This event was initially created in 2014 by the gaming journalist Geoff Keighley to award the best games released each year, but has steadily grown to be more of a showcase for announcements of the upcoming ones, mixed with a considerable amount of related advertisement, absorbing some of the mediatic space left by the now (probably) defunct E3. It’s safe to say that TGA is by now one of the most important events in this media, with a viewership of 103 millions in 2022, according to the organisation. As so, everyone is interested in having a small piece the three and half hours of the ceremony’s runtime, from the small indie studios to the big names. There’s a bit of everything in here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But let’s focus on what happened during this year’s edition. Who came out on top and who or what were the biggest disappointments? Let’s find out by nominating the winners and losers of the The Game Awards 2023.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winners&quot;&gt;Winners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;baldurs-gate-3&quot;&gt;Baldur’s Gate 3&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no way to deny it, Baldur’s Gate 3 was the indisputable winner of this year, claiming 6 awards in 9 nominations, including Game Of The Year. This feat was even more impressive if we consider the quality of the other nominees in every category it claimed, being this one of the most competitive years ever. I personally didn’t played it as I’m not that invested in Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons (in which this game is based of), but I believe all the acclaim was deserved. After all, it was arguably the best-received game this year, being truly consensual among critics and fans.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alan-wake-2&quot;&gt;Alan Wake 2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other game that collected a nice amount of little statues, with 3 awards in 8 nominations. Curiously, Alan Wake 2 was announced to the public precisely at The Game Awards, two years prior. Surely a must play for fans of survival horror.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sega&quot;&gt;Sega&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who would have thought that Sega would have the best announcement of this TGA? I didn’t, even thought they teased it a few days before. Sega has a precedent of overpromising and underdelivering, so I was cautious. Surprisingly this time the hype was justified. They announced FIVE new titles at once, from their repertoire of dormant franchises: Jet Set Radio, Crazy Taxi, Streets of Rage, Shinobi and Golden Axe. As a long time Sega fan, it’s impossible to not be excited with this. The only problem I saw was the fact they mentioned that this games were “now in development”, which means that we probably won’t see them anytime soon. One or two may come out later in 2024, but my hopes are low. To be fair, I don’t mind to wait. Kudos also to Atlus (which Sega owns), for showing new trailers for the two games I’m most eager to play next year: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4py4V5xwXWE&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q4bGNzXnKak&quot;&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0VHYLJR9pNg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The trailer was a bit cheesy, but the games revealed look promising.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hideo-kojima&quot;&gt;Hideo Kojima&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s well known that the mastermind behind Metal Gear Solid and Death Stranding has a good relationship with Geoff Keighley, which grants him a free pass to use TGA as its own marketing platform. At this point it would be a surprise to not see him on stage talking during several minutes about an upcoming project without showing anything substantial about it. This year we were presented with a game called “OD”, with the only thing shown being a tech demo of a few face animations. It was weird, in classic Kojima fashion. I don’t know if it was a win for the public in general, but for him it was for sure. See you next year Kojima-san.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;honorable-mention&quot;&gt;Honorable Mention&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nintendo&quot;&gt;Nintendo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With little to no presence during the event, Nintendo managed to sneakily snag 3 awards: Best Action / Adventure Game (The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom), Best Family Game (Super Mario Bros. Wonder) and Best Sim / Strategy Game (Pikmin 4), in a total of 15 nominations. A fair reward considering the great year they had in terms of releases. Regarding the future, Nintendo didn’t unveil the curtain, although their 2024 looks pretty slim so far. Probably not the right time for announcements, as they might have bigger fish to fry with their imminent upcoming system.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;losers&quot;&gt;Losers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marvels-spider-man-2&quot;&gt;Marvel’s Spider Man 2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sony’s sole horse for the silverware race lost in a spectacular way, taking home a staggering amount of zero awards, in 7 nominations. It was unfortunate, as the game actually looks good and should be fun to play, taking in consideration my knowledge of its predecessor. However, it was outclassed in every category it was nominated for. As I said before, this was a very competitive year and Spider Man 2 ended up being the colateral damage.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;starfield&quot;&gt;Starfield&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was already known that Starfield wouldn’t be in the discussion for a huge amount of awards, as it wasn’t even nominated for Game of the Year, but considering it was one of the most anticipated games of 2023, it’s disappointing to see Xbox and Bethesda’s newest crown jewel relegated to second plan, recieveing a single nomination for Best Role Playing Game. Even there it had the misfortue of encounter and lose to the inevitable Baldur’s Gate 3. Can’t say it was unfair, since the game’s reception was mixed overall, but Todd Howard surely must be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LyL5kKW5xAo&quot;&gt;a bit disapointed&lt;/a&gt; with this outcome. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;every-award-winner-on-stage&quot;&gt;Every award winner on stage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year during the winning speech for Best Performance, Christopher Judge, who portrayed Kratos in God of War Ragnarök, caught everyone by surprise by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ij0VUU6L1io&amp;amp;t=255s&quot;&gt;speaking uninterruptedly for eight minutes&lt;/a&gt;. It was clear that even the production wasn’t aware of what was happening back then, because this year they overcompensated for that little detour. This time around each award winner had no more than a single minute to deliver their speech before having a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/javierabegazo/status/1732975428237934964&quot;&gt;“Please wrap it up”&lt;/a&gt; message on the teleprompter. The Game Awards always had problems in balancing the show between the awards itself and the promotional side, with the balance tending more and more in favour of the later as the years go by. I would be lying if I said that I don’t care about those announcements, but to put in perspective, any of the several ads for Lego Fortnite or Honkai: Star Rail that ran during the event lasted longer than any winner speech.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vn_iJ7PBMJQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Poor Aonuma-san, barely had time to read his speech, not to mention his translator.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From the few interesting announcements, to the winners trimmed speeches, passing by the countless unnecessary ads (I know Lego Fortnite is a thing FFS, I saw the first ad), The Game Awards 2023 was a complete mixed bag. I hope Geoff takes his lessons from this year and turn this event into something truly great, because the potential is already there. Or probably give 20 minutes on stage to each winner to compensate for the overcompensation.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">Beside the usual festive season, the end of the year is now also marked by a more recent tradition, The Game Awards. This event was initially created in 2014 by the gaming journalist Geoff Keighley to award the best games released each year, but has steadily grown to be more of a showcase for announcements of the upcoming ones, mixed with a considerable amount of related advertisement, absorbing some of the mediatic space left by the now (probably) defunct E3. It’s safe to say that TGA is by now one of the most important events in this media, with a viewership of 103 millions in 2022, according to the organisation. As so, everyone is interested in having a small piece the three and half hours of the ceremony’s runtime, from the small indie studios to the big names. There’s a bit of everything in here. But let’s focus on what happened during this year’s edition. Who came out on top and who or what were the biggest disappointments? Let’s find out by nominating the winners and losers of the The Game Awards 2023.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyberpunk 2077</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/cyberpunk-2077" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyberpunk 2077" /><published>2023-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/cyberpunk-2077</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/cyberpunk-2077">&lt;p&gt;Saying that Cyberpunk 2077 had a terrible launch is an understatement. Back in late 2020, when the public finally got the chance to play it after several delays and an unsustainable hype surrounding it, they found a completely broken game. Not only it was a farcry from what the developers CD Projekt Red had promissed during all the years since the game was announced, but it was filled with a myriad of technical issues. The case was particularly bad with the PS4 and Xbox One versions, to the point of Sony removing it from their digital store until it reached a “playable” state.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I was one of the persons eager to play the game back then, but all the chaos surrounding it made me forget that idea, until recently. After find the PS4 version at a very good price, I decided to give it a chance and see by myself if it was still as broken, after a few years and countless bug fixing patches.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-this-a-rpg&quot;&gt;Is this a RPG?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a first glance, Cyberpunk 2077 may look like a futuristic Grand Theft Auto, as it was my expectation before playing it, but right from the beggining we understand that it isn’t quite the case. We play as a mercenary named “V”, that can be fully customized to our preference. The game even give us the option to choose one of three distinct backgrounds for our character. Sadly this only changes the early part of the game and a few extra dialog options. But nothing that took my enjoyment from the main plot, that opens in a fantastic way. It goes like this:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Our protagonist, V, is requested to steal an experimental biochip (that is essentially a cyberware implant) during one of their mercenary gigs. While most of the heist went relatively smooth, things turned for worse after they retrieve the chip, being ambushed by its owner’s security. While trying to escape, the chip protection case got damaged, with the only way for V to avoid its degradation being to insert it in their own body. They soon realise that the chip actually contained a soul of a deceased person ready to appropriate V’s body, erasing their own soul in the process. The person in question is Johnny Silverhand, portrayed by Keanu Reeves. From this point, the narrative focus on this mental struggle between two souls fighting over one body, with Silverhand appearing randomly in hallucinations, and in some cases taking full control for a brief moment.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I admit it was quite difficult to summarise the prologue, because there’s much more to it than this, but I don’t want to spoil everything to you. Actually, it was the density of this story and characters dialogs that made me realise that this was far from just an action game, or a shooter. At the same time, everything had a more steamlined feeling than your typical western RPG (comparing for example with any Bethesda Game Studios title). I usually get a bit overwhelmed when I have too many options to choose from, as so, for me Cyberpunk 2077 hit the right balance between linearity and freedom.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With all that said, beside the main story, there are several side quests worth exploring. Usually they are focused on specific characters or groups and span across multiple missions. Each side quest helps you to better understand the complex dynamic of Night City, the place where all this takes place. There are multiple factions fighting for their turf, corporation wars, all new kinds of addictions, and the cherry on top, a completely inefficient police department. The perfect recipe for a chaotic city full of friends, as long as your interests match theirs, and foes, ready to be decimated by a weapon of your choice.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-beauty-in-night-city&quot;&gt;The beauty in Night City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is one department where this game absolutely nails the park is the visuals. Every corner of Night City is very detailed and full of colourful neons. There is a certain joy to just wandering around the city during nighttime in a fast car, while listening some Lo-fi beats on &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/5r149kHSZvI?si=BaBXCwo8aheh2_Bu&amp;amp;t=657&quot;&gt;Pacific Dreams&lt;/a&gt;, one of the many radio stations with music composed specifically for this game. Even the areas outside the city itself, while not so dense in buildings and population, are visually stunning as well. Speaking on density, there lies the biggest issue with this game when played on Xbox One or PS4, as it was my case.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LMt_6VNBm2s&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ This mission is the best showcase of Cyberpunk 2077 great graphics and art direction.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-generational-problem&quot;&gt;A generational problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, Xbox One and PS4 were still pretty much alive, while its successors were still suffering from huge stock shortages. It made sense to release this game on both back then. Although, beside the bugs common to every platform, new and old, there was an underlying issue carved into the game core design that impeded it to perform well on those consoles. They were equipped by default with good ol’ HDD hard drives. What’s the issue with that, you ask? You see, those drives are very, very slow compared to the now standard SSDs. While navigating around the visually complex Night City, the game often freezes during a few seconds for the hard drive to catch up and load all the necessary assets to render everything visible to the eye. Of course this wasn’t an issue if the drive was fast enough to provide those assets on the fly. Luckily, there is a very obvious solution: upgrading the console’s HDD to a SSD. It makes a world of difference. With this setup, you can have a perfectly playable version of this incredible game on a system with 2013 specs. That on itself is a miracle.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is an elephant in the room though. This old systems didn’t received the latest 2.0 upgrade that revisioned some core game mechanics, neither the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cyberpunk.net/us/en/phantom-liberty&quot;&gt;Phantom Liberty&lt;/a&gt; expansion, so you will miss some content just like I did if the last-gen Xbox or Playstation consoles are your only options. But I assure you that even without that, Cyberpunk 2077 is totally worth playing, now that it’s a polished product.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engaging and complex main story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Side quests worth of exploring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Night City is visually impressive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Futuristic soundtrack fits really well in this universe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A SSD upgrade is a “must have” to play it on last-gen consoles
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things considered, Cyberpunk 2077 is an amazing and unforgetable experience that deserves its ongoing redemption story.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Saying that Cyberpunk 2077 had a terrible launch is an understatement. Back in late 2020, when the public finally got the chance to play it after several delays and an unsustainable hype surrounding it, they found a completely broken game. Not only it was a farcry from what the developers CD Projekt Red had promissed during all the years since the game was announced, but it was filled with a myriad of technical issues. The case was particularly bad with the PS4 and Xbox One versions, to the point of Sony removing it from their digital store until it reached a “playable” state. I was one of the persons eager to play the game back then, but all the chaos surrounding it made me forget that idea, until recently. After find the PS4 version at a very good price, I decided to give it a chance and see by myself if it was still as broken, after a few years and countless bug fixing patches.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ABXY review system</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/abxy-review-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ABXY review system" /><published>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/abxy-review-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/abxy-review-system">&lt;p&gt;Ah, game reviews. Just like in every other type of media review, there isn’t a single kind of content that can drive so much excitement, or ire (mostly ire), of the rabid fans of the piece subjected to scrutiny. No review is perfect or the source of universal truth, as everyone has their biases, including the people whose job is to write them. I also have my own bias, but in my case nobody pays me to write reviews, so I have no lobbies to please. I can guarantee you that at least.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how I will rate each game I review? That’s the question that nobody asked, but I will answer regardless. I’m not interested in complex rating systems, with decimal points, or scores for each aspect of the game. I find quite difficult to associate numbers to an experience in a logical way, so I will associate stars instead, just like this: ✦✧✧✧✧. This is an example of a 1 out of 5 star review, that in its essence is a numbered rating and invalidates everything I said so far. But at least, with only five rating tiers, I can correlate a specific feeling to each one of them. Which feelings you may ask? Allow me to explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bad&quot;&gt;Bad&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✧✧✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is somewhat obvious. This rating is for the kind of game that I didn’t enjoyed at all, but it still had some redeeming quality, as little as it could be comparing with all the other major issues, that pushed me at least to finish it. Otherwise I would simply drop it after a few minutes, without even considering writing a review about it. A game worth of this rating is &lt;strong&gt;Sonic R&lt;/strong&gt;. Its gameplay is absolutely hideous, but it was graced with one of the best soundtracks in the entire series.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1b8F1qa5-eM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Right from the title screen you can tell the music is good.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okay&quot;&gt;Okay&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✧✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is reserved for games that weren’t that obnoxiously bad or frustrating, but didn’t went anywhere particularly interesting or new, falling in the land of mediocrity. One relatively recent example of that is &lt;strong&gt;Mario Strikers: Battle League Football&lt;/strong&gt;. A game that looks and plays fine, but it isn’t captivating in the slightest, doing little to keep the players invested, either in single player or online.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/H85m53GeWZo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ At least the cutscenes look cool.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good&quot;&gt;Good&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The middle of the road. Now the subject was something far from bad, but still a few steps away of excellence. This are the kind of games that were entertaining during their playthrough, but lacked that special factor that elevate them to an unforgetable experience. For me, &lt;strong&gt;Marvel’s Spider Man&lt;/strong&gt; encapsulates well this feeling. A game with a sublime gameplay but a not so interesting plot or variety of things to do.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rfiLXMZE_Hw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Web slinging around New York feels admittedly satisfying.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we are talking seriously. Even if it’s not the highest rating, for a game to be “great”, it needs to get near perfection. But yet, a great game may lacks in some specific aspects that prevent them to reach that level. I experienced that with &lt;strong&gt;Mirror’s Edge&lt;/strong&gt;. The concept, music and artstyle were incredible, but the execution wasn’t refined enough.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jzj8OX1iUiY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ By far the best parkour game ever made.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpice&quot;&gt;Masterpice&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pinnacle of entertainment. This rating is reserved to games that I may consider my favourites of all time. Note that they might not be perfect for everyone, or even perfect on a technical standpoint, but they are perfect to me. &lt;strong&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild&lt;/strong&gt; is my most immediate example of a masterpice. I cannot even describe it in one sentence.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/JbhS4OXWNsE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Few moments in gaming beat the one when we observe Hyrule's landscape for the first time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This sums up how I will rate games here on ABXY. Of course, the rating is only part of the story, as it will be paired with a few paragraphs explaing why I decided to attribue it to the game in question.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for now. See you next time, on my first review here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Ah, game reviews. Just like in every other type of media review, there isn’t a single kind of content that can drive so much excitement, or ire (mostly ire), of the rabid fans of the piece subjected to scrutiny. No review is perfect or the source of universal truth, as everyone has their biases, including the people whose job is to write them. I also have my own bias, but in my case nobody pays me to write reviews, so I have no lobbies to please. I can guarantee you that at least.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to ABXY</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/welcome-to-abxy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to ABXY" /><published>2023-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/welcome-to-abxy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/welcome-to-abxy">&lt;p&gt;Hi, welcome to ABXY, my blog about gaming. Maybe “blog” is an outdated term, let’s call it an independent publication instead. Anyway, in case you don’t know who I am, let me put you up to speed.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I’m João, but most friends call me Chari. Videogames were always a special thing for me, even though that sentiment wasn’t shared by anyone in my family, who only saw them as way to waste time, or even an addiction. This appreciation wasn’t something inherited, even I can’t quite explain exactly how it happened, but I may point out my interest for every kind of visual and interactive media as a strong reason. It was not by chance that I became a designer and developer.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eventually my interest for the media had grown beside just playing the games. I become interested in knowing the history, the latest news and even how the industry worked. It was by then that I came to the conclusion that for me, gaming was more than a hobby. As so, I decided to start writing about the topic. My intention is obviously to share my views on them with everyone interested, but also to document my playthroughs, for sake of my own memory.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-can-you-expect-from-abxy&quot;&gt;What can you expect from ABXY?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviews&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
My main focus will be on reviewing games that I finish, considering most I play are single player. Don’t expect the most recent ones reviewed during its release window though, you have IGN, Gamespot and many other outlets for that. It can happen occasionally though, but even if I get a game on day one, I’m not going to torture myself with a speedrun just to write about it. New games are expensive, it’s a waste to rush them.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Monthly updates&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
By the end of each month I’ll do a quick recap of everything I played during that period. It will be something more brief, in form of first impressions or progress report for each game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Opinions&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Lastly, I also want to do some opinion articles, but more sporadically. I’ll only do this if I feel that I have something interesting, or funny, to say regarding the topics in question.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is my vision for ABXY. If it’s going to be exactly like I described it? I have no idea, but I hope you and the other few ones who end up here reading my rambles at least find them entertaining.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Hi, welcome to ABXY, my blog about gaming. Maybe “blog” is an outdated term, let’s call it an independent publication instead. Anyway, in case you don’t know who I am, let me put you up to speed. I’m João, but most friends call me Chari. Videogames were always a special thing for me, even though that sentiment wasn’t shared by anyone in my family, who only saw them as way to waste time, or even an addiction. This appreciation wasn’t something inherited, even I can’t quite explain exactly how it happened, but I may point out my interest for every kind of visual and interactive media as a strong reason. It was not by chance that I became a designer and developer. Eventually my interest for the media had grown beside just playing the games. I become interested in knowing the history, the latest news and even how the industry worked. It was by then that I came to the conclusion that for me, gaming was more than a hobby. As so, I decided to start writing about the topic. My intention is obviously to share my views on them with everyone interested, but also to document my playthroughs, for sake of my own memory.</summary></entry></feed>