<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://joaomarques.website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-27T12:25:29+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/feed.xml</id><title type="html">João Marques | Abxy</title><subtitle>UX/UI Designer &amp; Frontend developer. Author of the gaming blog ABXY.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A day at Gamescom 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A day at Gamescom 2024" /><published>2024-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/gamescom-24">&lt;p&gt;Since I started to follow with more attention the videogame industry, I had this somewhat farfetched dream of attending an E3, which was for around 20 years the pinnacle of the medium. That dream never came to life since the days of E3 are now long gone. While &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/the-game-awards-2023&quot;&gt;The Game Awards&lt;/a&gt; absorbed some of the space left by it for the big and surprising game reveals, it was Gamescom who assumed the role of the biggest gaming conference in the world, growing considerably year by year in terms of attendance and relevance to the industry.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For me that was perfect, since a trip from Portugal to Germany, where the Gamescom is hosted, was way shorter and cheaper than to the United States. The dream was back on in a more attainable form - a win-win situation. With that in mind, I decided that this would be the year where I would attend Gamescom for the first time. I’m here now to tell you how it went.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-logistics&quot;&gt;The logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to an event of this magnitude required some preparation. From the accomodation to the experience while visiting it, many aspects had to be considered to take the most out of the day. This were my main considerations:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cologne, the city in the western part of Germany where all this happens, is a very expensive city. Flight directly to there and stay at the city can become extremely costly. I went for the most logical and affordable solution by staying at the neighbour city of Bonn, 20 minutes away by train. Luckily the event ticket came with a free transport pass for the region during the day of attendance, covering the commute expenses.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When entering the venue of Gamescom, one thing became abundantly clear: all food and drinks in there were also ridiculously expensive. I came prepared for that though. After a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Gamescom/comments/wvm828/can_i_take_food_with_me/&quot;&gt;quick search on Reddit&lt;/a&gt; I found out that consumables from outside were allowed, as long as they weren’t alcoholic or contained in glass. I was able to save some money and time as well, as I took the chance to eat during the queues to try some game demos.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was difficult to visit the entire venue in just one day. Not only it was massive in terms of area, but moving from hall to hall was a challenge on itself due to the massive crowds. I did a plan beforehand in order to prioritise what I really wanted to see and experience, but outside of that I simply didn’t have enough time to explore more what else Gamescom had to offer. In retrospective, two days would be the ideal timeframe to a more complete insight on the whole event.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-event&quot;&gt;The event&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gamescom had a lot of things to offer for a single day, to a point of being almost overwhelming. There were merchandise and artist alleys, cosplay contests, retro gaming areas, game tournaments, meet and greets, talks with game creators and many more. However, the main draw of the event was without doubt what they called of “Entertainment area”, where the companies present there put their best suits and presented their upcoming games in gigantic, colorful and captivating booths. I didn’t have opportunity to visit all them, but it was still possible to get some insights from an overall perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was an evident huge investment from asian companies besides Japan, most noticably the south korean Krafton, that was there mainly to promote their new social simulation game &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H6x864OOErk&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;InZOI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by flexing its powerful character creation tool. Hoyoverse from China also had a strong representation, promoting their hallmark games &lt;strong&gt;Genshin Impact&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Honkai: Star Rail&lt;/strong&gt;, beside their recently released &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-b_37whBVvA&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zenless Zone Zero&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by offering enormous gift bags that turned their visitors into mobile outdors. Really clever, I must admit.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Household names like Ubisoft or Capcom also had a noticable presence there. The first was promoting &lt;strong&gt;Assassin’s Creed Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Star Wars Outlaws&lt;/strong&gt; while the latter put their money almost entirely on &lt;strong&gt;Monster Hunter Wilds&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually, the promotion for that particular game was so heavy that there were outdoors everywhere inviting people to their booth, even outside the boundaries of the venue, being spread around the digital advertisement panels of the city itself. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the big three console manufacturers, the only one who was there in a substancial form was Microsoft, showcasing &lt;strong&gt;Avowed&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Indiana Jones and The Great Circle&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Starfield Shattered Space&lt;/strong&gt;, to name a few. Sony was nowhere to be seen and Nintendo presence was limited to the Indie hall, supporting a few developers to showcase their titles for the Switch. Sony’s absense seems logical as they don’t have any upcoming flagship title, but Nintendo actually have a new Zelda about to be released, it seemed odd for them to not take the chance to promote it. I assume they are saving all their PR efforts to the reveal of their next system.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside the entertainment area, there were also a lot of interesting things to explore on the indie and retro gaming areas. On the indie one, there were simply too many games to try out, it was impossible to catch everything. I was able to briefly try two titles, &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1830430/Grimoire_Groves/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grimoire Groves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1594060/Victory_Heat_Rally/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victory Heat Rally&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but both seemed to be still in a rough state to be honest. On the retro gaming area, there were a few booths of projects and entities dedicated to the subject, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/retrogamer_mag&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retro Gaming Magazine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, selling some of their editions (sadly only in german), and the Sega Saturn focused podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/6Uj3gD5KMQ4r4dJOjsknRF&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHIRO!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whose booth was obviously composed by several Saturns ready to be played. Unfortuately I didn’t spend as much time as I would like in this areas, but I will pay more attention to them if I ever return to the Gamescom in a future edition.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-demos&quot;&gt;The demos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s better than see new games? Playing them. I had the opportunity to watch exclusive gameplay of two titles from Bethesda and try out in first hand two other from Sega/Atlus. Here are my impressions from each one of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starfield Shattered Space:&lt;/strong&gt; This is an expansion that promises to deliver in areas where the base game was severly critizised for, particularly the environmental design, that will be composed by a handful of carefully crafted planets instead of a multitude of randomly generated ones, and the story. In visual terms, every footage they’ve shown looked way more eye catchy than everything the game offered before.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indiana Jones and The Great Circle:&lt;/strong&gt; A brand new game focused on the famous movie franchise where we impersonate a digital recreation of a young Harrison Ford, from a first person perspective. I have some reservations regarding that first person view, as it doesn’t look ideal for platforming. On the other hand, it’s the best choice for shooting and puzzle solving. I wonder how they will integrate seamlessly all this mechanics in the final product.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metaphor: ReFantazio:&lt;/strong&gt; This was by far the game I was most anticipating to play at Gamescom. Being from Atlus, it carries a lot of heritage from their previous games, starting by its development team, lead by the director of Persona 3, 4 and 5. Metaphor however is set in a medieval fantasy universe, contrasting with the contemporary setting of Persona. During the 15 minutes demo, I was able to experience a bit of the dungeon exploration and combat, that introduces a action oriented style, combined with the traditional turn-based one. From my limited experience, it works perfectly and it will make grinding much more fun and effortless. In the audio-visual department I have nothing but praise. In my opinion few companies make better game user interfaces than Atlus and Metaphor is here to prove it once again.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vgtv1orwhmU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ In the Metaphor: ReFantazio demo it was possible to explore a dungeon and even fight a boss.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sonic x Shadow Generations:&lt;/strong&gt; The last game I tried out during my time at Gamescom. Sonic Generations is essentially a remaster of the 2011 original for modern platforms, but what makes it interesting even for me, having played it back in the day, is the all new Shadow Generations. The model seems to be similar to Super Mario 3D World + Bowser’s Fury, essentially a compilation of two separated, yet related games. The demo available allowed me to experience two levels of each and my lasting impression of the new Shadow levels was really positive. They look great and play great, what more can I ask?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6lw7EAV-by4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The new Shadow levels are for sure the most interesting part of this new Sonic x Shadow Generations.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, going to the Gamescom was a fulfilling experience, even if a bit tiresome and overwhelming at points. I’m not sure if I’ll return next year, but I know (and I hope) this won’t be my last time here.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lastly, I also participated on the latest episode of The Games Tome podcast, where I talked more in depth about everything I mentioned here (in 🇵🇹).
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B0MnYMpNpT8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ My participation at The Games Tome podcast, in an episode dedicated to this edition of the Gamescom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">Since I started to follow with more attention the videogame industry, I had this somewhat farfetched dream of attending an E3, which was for around 20 years the pinnacle of the medium. That dream never came to life since the days of E3 are now long gone. While The Game Awards absorbed some of the space left by it for the big and surprising game reveals, it was Gamescom who assumed the role of the biggest gaming conference in the world, growing considerably year by year in terms of attendance and relevance to the industry. For me that was perfect, since a trip from Portugal to Germany, where the Gamescom is hosted, was way shorter and cheaper than to the United States. The dream was back on in a more attainable form - a win-win situation. With that in mind, I decided that this would be the year where I would attend Gamescom for the first time. I’m here now to tell you how it went. The logistics</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – July 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – July 2024" /><published>2024-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jul-24">&lt;p&gt;Here we are, August. As each month goes by, I have less ideas on what to write in this introduction paragraph. Let’s focus on what really matters here, the games:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I predicted on my last &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Played this month&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I got fully invested on Metal Gear Solid 2 and its completely bonkers plot. If the first MGS played a bit with fourth wall breaks and meta concepts, this one was all about them. This is the kind of game that let you thinking for hours about what you just witnessed after the credits roll. I’ll leave it like this for now, as I will save the details for the upcoming review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn-based strategy / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finished this month the second and possibly last game in the Mario + Rabbids series, as Davide Soliani, the director of both games, &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/DavideSoliani/status/1816050633343938597&quot;&gt;announced his departure from Ubisoft&lt;/a&gt;. It was kind of poetic to finish the game just a couple days before this announcement, as it was also my end of cycle with this series. As for Sparks of Hope itself, I’ll save my opinions for an eventual review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 3: Snake Eater&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, more Metal Gear. For this one my expectations are unreasonably high, as it’s generally considered the peak of the series. For now, it’s still to early for me to have any sort of opinion, but next month I’ll probably have something to say about it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Ridge Racer 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racing / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My side project of this month was the restoration of a PSP. I had Ridge Racer 2 as the default game to test the system as I was fixing it. Without even noticing, I ended up playing (and winning) a couple of Grand Prix in it. It’s such a shame this series is pretty much dead nowadays, because there is no recent racing game that comes even close to capture its iconic style.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PSP
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I went to such lengths to restore a PSP was precisely to continue my Persona journey. Sony’s first portable gaming system was blessed with not one but four Persona games during its time! I decided to start by the beginning, with the very first game (whose PSP version is a port of the PS1 original). Despite my short experience with it, I can already tell that this one is a very different beast from the others that I already played. One thing it has in common with those is its absolute &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nuKpIDf4U_o&amp;amp;list=PLX4JWB4HZSn9uFPQ2zTEbl5l72JamF3wO&quot;&gt;banger of soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;. Seriously, it’s hard to think of another series that is consistently spectacular on this aspect.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for July! For next month, I’ll be at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gamescom.global/en&quot;&gt;Gamescom&lt;/a&gt; (and Germany by extension) for the first time! I’ll do an article about my experience for sure. See ya!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Here we are, August. As each month goes by, I have less ideas on what to write in this introduction paragraph. Let’s focus on what really matters here, the games:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mother 3</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mother 3" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/mother-3">&lt;p&gt;Mother is arguably one of the most fascinating series from Nintendo’s long and iconic catalogue. When I say this, I’m not only referring to the games themselves but how they came to life. It was born out of the mind of Shigesato Itoi, a multi-talented Japanese celebrity who wanted to create an RPG based on a contemporary setting, unlike anything else that existed until that point, in the late 1980s. After some reluctance, he was able to convince Nintendo to work on his game. Mother, as it was named by Itoi himself, was released in Japan in 1989, being a success of sales and critics. However, it was its sequel that solidified the series’ cult status.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Released five long years later, due to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ign.com/articles/2019/07/23/how-satoru-iwata-saved-earthbound-from-development-hell&quot;&gt;complex development cycle salvaged by the then Nintendo’s future president Satoru Iwata&lt;/a&gt;, Mother 2 was also positively received by Japanese audiences. Unfortunately, the same couldn’t be said about its international release, renamed as EarthBound. By 1995 standards, the game was perceived as outdated due to its simplistic and somewhat childish pixel-art style, resulting in mixed reviews and really poor sales outside its origin country. However, not many years later, with the advent of the internet and emulation, as well as a cameo in the Super Smash Bros. series, EarthBound gained a second life. People started to properly appreciate it outside the biased conventions of the media outlets at the time, to the point that it is nowadays considered one of the very best games ever made.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This leads us to Mother 3, which had an even more troubled development. It was initially conceived as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6pcd9VnnXSQ&quot;&gt;Nintendo 64 title with a 3D engine&lt;/a&gt;, but the scale and complexity of the project caused multiple delays, until it was officially canceled in 2000. But all hope wasn’t lost, because a few years later the development was rebooted for the Gameboy Advance, with visuals more in line with its predecessor, being finally released in 2006… exclusively in Japan.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Luckily for those who can’t read Japanese, a group of dedicated fans created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://mother3.fobby.net/&quot;&gt;English translation&lt;/a&gt;. It was precisely thanks to this translation that I was able to play this incredible game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;family-matters&quot;&gt;Family matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother 3 is focused around a young boy named Lucas and his family, who live in a small rural town named Tazmily, where everyone is friendly and respectful to each other. Everything is good until the day the village is invaded by some mysterious and hostile military forces. Amidst all the chaos caused by them, something terrible happens to Hinawa and Claus, the mother and twin brother of Lucas respectively. The story then jumps to a period three years after that tragic event. By then, the depth of the writing, scenario, and character development becomes evident. We still find most of the people we met during the epilogue, but their lives changed drastically since then, as did the village itself. Tazmily became much more industrialized and its people more individualistic. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tazmily is just the tip of the iceberg on everything Mother 3 has to offer in terms of narrative. There are a lot of smaller stories within the village itself, but me writing about all of them not only would make this review unbearably huge, as it wouldn’t do them justice. Actually, there is a particular aspect in this game that is quite unusual for a story-driven RPG - During most of it, we don’t have even the slightest clue about our end goal, we are just following a succession of random events, but damn, the journey is so gripping. Most of the merit is on the brilliant writing for the small moments, being them happy, sad, or plain funny, especially when they come at the most unexpected times. How a simple game can convey such strong emotions is something that I can’t quite explain, but even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z8YaKuWLvGs&quot;&gt;Nintendo’s marketing team knew&lt;/a&gt; it was Mother 3’s &lt;em&gt;secret sauce&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7YnbMbI8aKE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The first chapter of Mother 3 ends in a tragic tone and with a lot of mysteries to uncover.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-world-of-quirkiness&quot;&gt;A world of quirkiness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this review has been focused exclusively on storytelling so far, Mother 3 has more to offer than that. In terms of gameplay, it’s a traditional RPG, but with a few twists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The party:&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of a consistent group of characters, our party changes constantly according to the story progress. We only get the “definitive” party by the penultimate chapter. That chapter is also by far the longest one, taking almost half of the game’s runtime.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The combat:&lt;/strong&gt; For the most part, it follows the traditional turn-based system, where each character can attack physically or psychically (the equivalent of a magic power), defend, or use items. The first twist comes in the way the HP counter works. When an enemy attacks, instead of dealing all the damage at once to a character, their HP starts to roll down gradually, like a car odometer, but in reverse. By acting fast it’s possible to avoid what would be otherwise a certain death, by healing before the counter reaches zero. If we choose to defend, the counter also rolls slower than usual. The other interesting twist in the game’s combat is the timed attack mechanic. By timing the attacks to the beat of the background music, our characters can deal extra hits (and do a jamming session as a bonus). Mastering this technique is fundamental to beat certain bosses, as some of them can be &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The enemies:&lt;/strong&gt; While not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; enemies are super weird, many of them are. A perfect example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UE3BUoWGmEw&quot;&gt;Negative Man&lt;/a&gt;, a rectangular creature that seems to be incredibly depressed and implores us to kill it. Although, what’s even more captivating than the characters themselves, is how they are presented - as a static image over a psychedelic background animation. All their interactions are conveyed through visual effects and micro-interactions in the HUD. Conceptually it may look like a terrible idea, but the execution was inexplicably flawless.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The items:&lt;/strong&gt; There are no swords or guns in Mother 3. Most items found in the game are mundane objects. Yo-Yos, sticks, and even rolled pamphlets serve as weapons, for example. This gives an overall sense of groundedness to the game, even when it goes to places way far detached from reality.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All this beautiful weirdness is amplified by an equally beautiful and weird soundtrack, comprised of more than 200 unique songs! From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q3Xsy_Ual8o&quot;&gt;happy&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XU4AK4NZ2Q&quot;&gt;sad&lt;/a&gt; themes, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RK960EqwS1Q&quot;&gt;something in between&lt;/a&gt;, the musical variety present here is impressive.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3a_IuOffRYw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Mother 3 was re-released on the Nintendo Switch Online service exclusively in Japan, yet again.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I decided to play this game my expectations were already high, even so, it was able to surprise me in a positive way many times during my journey with it. I couldn’t ask for more. Mother 3 is brilliant in its uniqueness.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quirky sense of humor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple and yet very emotional story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expect the unexpected all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beautiful and expansive soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Superb fan translation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few unbalanced difficulty spikes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clunky item management
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;masterpiece&quot;&gt;Masterpiece&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✦&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t describe Mother 3 in one sentence, there’s so much more to it than meets the eye. If your thing is story-driven games, just do a favor to yourself and play it. It’s all I can say.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Mother is arguably one of the most fascinating series from Nintendo’s long and iconic catalogue. When I say this, I’m not only referring to the games themselves but how they came to life. It was born out of the mind of Shigesato Itoi, a multi-talented Japanese celebrity who wanted to create an RPG based on a contemporary setting, unlike anything else that existed until that point, in the late 1980s. After some reluctance, he was able to convince Nintendo to work on his game. Mother, as it was named by Itoi himself, was released in Japan in 1989, being a success of sales and critics. However, it was its sequel that solidified the series’ cult status. Released five long years later, due to a complex development cycle salvaged by the then Nintendo’s future president Satoru Iwata, Mother 2 was also positively received by Japanese audiences. Unfortunately, the same couldn’t be said about its international release, renamed as EarthBound. By 1995 standards, the game was perceived as outdated due to its simplistic and somewhat childish pixel-art style, resulting in mixed reviews and really poor sales outside its origin country. However, not many years later, with the advent of the internet and emulation, as well as a cameo in the Super Smash Bros. series, EarthBound gained a second life. People started to properly appreciate it outside the biased conventions of the media outlets at the time, to the point that it is nowadays considered one of the very best games ever made. This leads us to Mother 3, which had an even more troubled development. It was initially conceived as a Nintendo 64 title with a 3D engine, but the scale and complexity of the project caused multiple delays, until it was officially canceled in 2000. But all hope wasn’t lost, because a few years later the development was rebooted for the Gameboy Advance, with visuals more in line with its predecessor, being finally released in 2006… exclusively in Japan. Luckily for those who can’t read Japanese, a group of dedicated fans created an English translation. It was precisely thanks to this translation that I was able to play this incredible game. Family matters</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – June 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – June 2024" /><published>2024-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-jun-24">&lt;p&gt;For the first time since January, I was able to publish at least two game reviews here at ABXY! To the ones who’ve read them, thank you. I hope you like the stuff I wrote, even if sometimes it’s nonsense gibberish. By the way, feel free to give feedback if you have any (I believe I have my X profile on the footer)! Anyway, this month was also prolific in terms of games finished, which means more reviews to write. It’s a never ending circle, what have I done…
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first game I finished this month. This is one I’ll never forget, for how funny and emotional it was. I’ll save the details for a full review, but you can count on a “Masterpiece” evaluation.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Sonic Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Sega Dreamcast
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the very same day, I also finished Sonic Adventure. You can already read &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-adventure&quot;&gt;my review&lt;/a&gt; of it!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Paper Mario: The Thousand-Year Door&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a game that I intended to play on its original GameCube version, but then I found the recently released Switch remaster at a good price and decided to go for it. I only played for a couple of hours, but it was enough to defeat the first boss. I will keep this one on hold until I finish the other games I have in progress.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mario + Rabbids Sparks of Hope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn-based strategy / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this game last year as a birthday gift for myself, but it didn’t click for me as its predecessor (Mario + Rabbids Kingdom Battle) even after playing until almost half of its campaign. In an effort to finish games I had in progress, I decided to give it a second chance. I’m glad I did it, as I was able to ignore the things I didn’t like before and focus on the good ones, in particular the unique combat system that blends turn-based with real-time strategy.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;EA FC 24&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football simulation / Nintendo Switch
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Euro time! Or it was, until Portugal and every underdog I was rooting for were eliminated. But before that, I was able to do a run with Ronaldo and company in EA FC 24 and lift the trophy. Case to say that in my simulation the captain was the best scorer of the tournament, which unfortunately proved to be a shocking departure from reality.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Metal Gear Solid 2: Sons of Liberty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / PS3
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m back to the biggest Kojima’s fever dream! I needed some time away from the Metal Gear Solid series to properly assimilate the first game, but now I’m ready to embrace its sequel.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And that’s all for June. During July I’ll probably be fully invested in Metal Gear and all its craziness. I’ll tell you how it went next month.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">For the first time since January, I was able to publish at least two game reviews here at ABXY! To the ones who’ve read them, thank you. I hope you like the stuff I wrote, even if sometimes it’s nonsense gibberish. By the way, feel free to give feedback if you have any (I believe I have my X profile on the footer)! Anyway, this month was also prolific in terms of games finished, which means more reviews to write. It’s a never ending circle, what have I done…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sonic Adventure</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-adventure" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sonic Adventure" /><published>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-adventure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/sonic-adventure">&lt;p&gt;I’ll start this review by saying that I’m a huge Sonic fan. I grew up with the classic trilogy games (&amp;amp; Knuckles), I had a great time with some of the less loved ones, such as Sonic 3D Blast, and even pre-ordered Sonic Frontiers! Do you know how dumb it is to pre-order a Sonic game, knowing that there is a great chance for it to be mediocre and have a massive price cut one month later? I’m that type of fan. However, I’d never played Sonic Adventure until the end before. For some reason I never got very far in my previous attempts, losing interest after the first couple of stages. This time around, I decided to give it a real chance and find why many other fans have it in such high regard. After completing all the six different campaigns present in the game I was able to understand why, but only thanks to hefty doses of context and resilience.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-all-about-chaos&quot;&gt;It’s all about Chaos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic Adventure was possibly the biggest pivot in the series history and consequently one of its most important games. When it came out in late 1998 for the Sega Dreamcast, a system that was a generational leap comparing with the Playstation and Nintendo 64, it was a graphical showpiece with large 3D environments, realistic textures and detailed character models. The characters themselves also received an extensive re-design and voice acting, allowing Sonic Team (the development team behind this game) to give them proper personalities and create more ambitious narratives. Gone was the &lt;em&gt;Classic Sonic&lt;/em&gt;, this was the beginning of the &lt;em&gt;Modern Sonic&lt;/em&gt; era.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Speaking of narratives, the one presented here is definitely the backbone of this game. As soon as we boot it up, we are presented with six different playable characters with distinct campaigns, although only Sonic is available at the start. As we progress in Sonic’s campaign, which is the &lt;em&gt;main course&lt;/em&gt; so to speak, we progressively unlock the other ones as their paths cross with the main character during the game events. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sonic’s story follows the same line of previous games, but with a new threat. Eggman wants to steal the Chaos Emeralds and use their power to conquer the world. To achieve it he uses a strange liquid creature named Chaos, that has the power to absorb the aforementioned emeralds and become even stronger. By facing Chaos multiple times during Sonic’s campaign we get the feeling that there’s something to uncover about it, but his story ends before reaching any conclusion. It turns out that defeating Eggman it’s just the tip of the iceberg. The real meat of it (yes, I’m using another food analogy in this article for no reason) is hidden in the other five campaigns. Pretty much like season 4 of Arrested Development (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0367279/episodes/?season=4&quot;&gt;the original one&lt;/a&gt;, not the awful remixed version), each character provides an unique POV on a narrative where all of them participate together. Uncovering the truth behind Chaos is a game on itself, as the pace and deliver of this story is quite unconventional. Even so, in some part is less frustrating than playing the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; game.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zTonLUzwkX8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Sonic Adventure's intro cutscene presents us Chaos in its most intimidating form.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;big-problems&quot;&gt;Big problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before Sonic’s campaign is the main focus here, and it shows. It’s the longest one in the game, composed of ten stages with the typical goal of going from A to B as fast as possible and a few boss battles in between. For the most part the stages are very well designed for Sonic’s precise and satisfying momentum-based controls, but it’s not too difficult to find issues. Quite often during my playthrough Sonic got stuck in some environmental detail, being it a wall, a rock or even the floor, causing him to glitch for a few seconds. This issue, usually called “clipping”, is a common thing in video games, but ideally it’s something very ocasional. Here it happens all the time. Maybe it’s a skill issue, but it’s a bad sign when the game breaks so easily when we go off rails. Speaking of that, I also have to mention the dynamic camera system of this game. Some specific points of each stage trigger a camera position and angle change, in theory to help the player see where they need to go next. But there is one problem. While the stages aren’t 100% linear, the camera only follows a single route. Exploring alternative paths while fighting the camera is beyond frustrating, even more so with a blazing fast character like Sonic.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FR86QgC3eiE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ This level is the epitome of Sonic Adventure: Great music, interesting concept and level layout, clipping issues left and right, absolutely terrible camera.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Sonic portion of Sonic Adventure has its problems, but its highlights almost overshadow them. I could end up here my review with this positive note, but unfortunately there’s much more to it. The &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; five campaigns to be more specific. To avoid bore you to death, I’ll keep it short and sweet and summarize each one of them in a few sentences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tails:&lt;/strong&gt; He tries to overcome his dependency on his best buddy Sonic by racing him on a few stages, but Tails flying ability is so OP that not even the &lt;em&gt;speed of sound&lt;/em&gt; is enough to overcome it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knuckles:&lt;/strong&gt; His campaign consists in boring treasure hunts on stages that clearly weren’t designed for that purpose.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amy:&lt;/strong&gt; Another character who wants emancipation from Sonic (good for her), but at least her story is a bit more interesting. Oh, and she has a hammer to destroy some Eggman’s robots.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E-102 Gamma:&lt;/strong&gt; One of Eggman’s robots. It has the best story in the game to be honest, it’s just a shame it’s so short. Its gameplay isn’t bad either, be it all about shooting targets with a lock-on mechanism.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big the Cat:&lt;/strong&gt; Hope you like bad fishing mini-games, because that’s all we do here. I was this close (imagine me pinching my fingers) to give up at this point. To add insult to the injury, his story contributes in absolutely nothing to the overarching narrative. Seriously, who thought this was a good idea?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9MUxqwK6LjU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Big the Cat's campaign is undoubtedly the worst part of Sonic Adventure.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One thing in common with all campaigns is a freely explorable overworld. A cool idea in theory, but very poorly executed. To advance from stage to stage we first need to figure out where should we go or what should we do. It turns out that more often than not it isn’t exactly clear. We have a few hints spread around the overworld, but sometimes not even those are enough. I had to consult a walkthrough in several ocasions as I wasn’t thrilled to figure it out on my own.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The most positive aspect of Sonic Adventure is that Sonic Team undestood what worked and what didn’t, resulting in a much improved sequel, without overworlds or fishing mini games, in Sonic Adventure 2. But that’s a story for another day.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layered and complex narrative across all the campaigns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonic’s precise controls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too many clipping issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The objectives to progress in the game aren’t always clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most obnoxious dynamic camera I ever saw in a videogame&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Big the Cat campaign
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okay&quot;&gt;Okay&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✧✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic Adventure had the merit of pushing Sega’s mascot into a new dimension and defining much of what the series is to this day. However, as a videogame on its own, it has too many rough edges to be an entirely enjoyable experience.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I’ll start this review by saying that I’m a huge Sonic fan. I grew up with the classic trilogy games (&amp;amp; Knuckles), I had a great time with some of the less loved ones, such as Sonic 3D Blast, and even pre-ordered Sonic Frontiers! Do you know how dumb it is to pre-order a Sonic game, knowing that there is a great chance for it to be mediocre and have a massive price cut one month later? I’m that type of fan. However, I’d never played Sonic Adventure until the end before. For some reason I never got very far in my previous attempts, losing interest after the first couple of stages. This time around, I decided to give it a real chance and find why many other fans have it in such high regard. After completing all the six different campaigns present in the game I was able to understand why, but only thanks to hefty doses of context and resilience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Persona 3 Reload</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-3-reload" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Persona 3 Reload" /><published>2024-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-3-reload</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-3-reload">&lt;p&gt;If you have been following this blog, you knew this review was coming. As this is the game I was anticipating the most this year, I didn’t want to rush it and guarantee that I had my sweet time with it. The result of that was a sense of closure after 90 hours of gameplay spread around 4 months. But what is so special about Persona 3 Reload to make me go to such lengths? You see, &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-4-golden&quot;&gt;Persona 4 Golden&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/persona-5-royal&quot;&gt;Persona 5 Royal&lt;/a&gt; were two of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://joaomarques.website/abxy/my-2023-in-gaming&quot;&gt;top 3 games from last year&lt;/a&gt;. Their unique formula of dungeon crawling mixed with social simulation elements had its inception precisely with 2006’s Persona 3. While its story and concept remained very interesting, every other element of it was naturally outclassed by its successors. That’s why when a remake of it was announced last year, it felt like a match made in heaven for us Persona fans: one of the most interesting narratives in the series combined with all the best gameplay features from P4 and P5 (mostly P5).
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Be aware that since I didn’t play the original game (or any of its re-editions), this will be as much as a review for this particular remake as for Persona 3 itself. All the knowledge I have of the original versions came from research.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-darkest-hour&quot;&gt;The darkest hour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Persona 3 starts with the game’s protagonist arriving at a school dormitory in Tatsumi Port Island, the place where he will live for the next year along some other students. Initially, we don’t know much about this school or the island itself, but soon we realise that something fishy is going on, because right on the first night, as the clock hits the midnight, we enter in a somber reality where the sky becomes green and everyone except a few individuals transform into coffins (yes, you read it right). This reality is known as the &lt;strong&gt;Dark Hour&lt;/strong&gt; and our protagonist, as all the dormitory residents, are some of the lucky ones that are fully awaken during it. To make things worse, during the Dark Hour, the school is transformed into a gigantic tower by the name of Tartarus.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As the story quickly reveals, those students didn’t end up in the same dormitory by accident. They were gathered purposely to bond as a team and defeat the evil shadows who roams around the 264 floors of Tartarus, as to uncover its origin and purpose. Being awake during the Dark Hour comes with the perk of being able to summon a Persona, a creature that is the materialization of the inner self and it possesses great powers. As such, these students are better equipped for the job than anyone.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VsMvSZeiKmw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ Meet the S.E.E.S., the group of students that fight shadows during the Dark Hour.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
During all the other hours of the day, we experience our protagonist and all the other student’s daily life, while going to school, meeting with people, doing part-time jobs and more. The usual gist of this series. More the characters we meet during the day, better the perks we have in the Dark Hour.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-moon&quot;&gt;New moon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remake of Persona 3 was something that was highly requested by the fans after the unprecedented success of Persona 5, in 2016. Many of them wondered what it would be of that game with all the graphical improvements and quality of life features of the latest iteration. This year Atlus finally attended the request with great success, I may say.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Persona 3 Reload is a complete graphical overhaul of the original. All the scenarios, character art, menus and everything you can think of were vastly improved and highly stylized. Everything in this game just looks cool. The already amazing soundtrack was also improved, with all the original themes being remade and with the addition of a few new ones, such as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/3znIACSXPLn3HFCf7moZ28?si=c9b1bf6a0c794c36&quot;&gt;new battle theme&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border-radius:12px&quot; src=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/20Bf2RVERC5Bc2eo3vyvJv?utm_source=generator&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;152&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From a gameplay perspective, apart the expected improvements, this remake is very faithful to the source material, for better or worse. All the key events and game calendar are untouched, as all its social links.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The social links, also known as “confidants” in Persona 5, are an essential element of this series formula, arguably its most iconic even. They consist in friendship ranking systems for each character we meet during the game, with interaction episodes that can level them up. It happens that Persona 3 was the first game to introduce this mechanic, and as with any first iteration of anything, it isn’t perfect. Some of the stories told during those interactions are painfully boring or just dumb, and not even in a funny way. The most aggravating example for me was this classmate we meet that really wants to date his teacher. To advance his social link, his endeavor needs to be encouraged. Obviously while doing that I was going deeply against my intuition. But probably that’s the message the game wants to convey, that sometimes we need to put on a mask to make some friends, who knows. Thankfully Reload introduces a few (much more interesting) extra episodes with some characters that didn’t have social links on the original game. I just wished they touched up the existent social links to make them as good as this new episodes, but I understand why they didn’t.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4py4V5xwXWE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ A glance into the two sides of Persona 3 Reload: the social link episodes during the day and the combat against shadows during the Dark Hour.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Other less positive aspect I noticed during my playthrough was some lack of balance in the gameplay activities. The days in a Persona game are divided into time slots, with the majority of them having two of those slots free for any activity of our choice, being them the afternoon and evening. If we want to visit the Dark Hour, which is fundamental for the game progress, the clock automatically skips the evening slot of the current day. Because of that the original game didn’t have a lot of activities allocated for that slot, to give the players enough time to explore the Dark Hour without missing anything. However, Reload is considerably easier than the original game, requiring less time to reach the goals during the Dark Hour. That made the lack of nighttime activities very evident, specially in the last months of the calendar.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While this last paragraphs sounded too negative, my lasting impressions of Persona 3 Reload are very positive. The only problem was my incredibly high expectations, set by my experience with Persona 4 and 5. I believe I would be more reasonable if P3R was my first Persona game, but because I already know where the series can go in terms of gameplay and storytelling, I ended up being a tiny bit underwhelmed.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arguably the darkest story in the series&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unapologetically stylish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredible soundtrack, as usual for Atlus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Superb voice acting for all characters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many social links stories aren’t great&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not much gameplay variety in the latter part of the game
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persona 3 Reload is undoubtedly a great remake, improving many outdated aspects of the original game, while keeping the dark and tragic narrative intact. However, by being faithful to the source material, some lackluster elements of it made it to this new reincarnation.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">If you have been following this blog, you knew this review was coming. As this is the game I was anticipating the most this year, I didn’t want to rush it and guarantee that I had my sweet time with it. The result of that was a sense of closure after 90 hours of gameplay spread around 4 months. But what is so special about Persona 3 Reload to make me go to such lengths? You see, Persona 4 Golden and Persona 5 Royal were two of my top 3 games from last year. Their unique formula of dungeon crawling mixed with social simulation elements had its inception precisely with 2006’s Persona 3. While its story and concept remained very interesting, every other element of it was naturally outclassed by its successors. That’s why when a remake of it was announced last year, it felt like a match made in heaven for us Persona fans: one of the most interesting narratives in the series combined with all the best gameplay features from P4 and P5 (mostly P5). Be aware that since I didn’t play the original game (or any of its re-editions), this will be as much as a review for this particular remake as for Persona 3 itself. All the knowledge I have of the original versions came from research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – May 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-may-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – May 2024" /><published>2024-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-may-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-may-24">&lt;p&gt;Here we are again, another month where almost all my playtime was absorbed by the same game. Luckily it was the last one! There was still some time to play a few more things, but not as many as I wanted. Anyway, here’s what I played in May:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s done, once and for all! 90 hours spread across 4 months it was all it took to finish this game. I was even very, very close to snag the platinum trophy, missing one single achievement that required starting the game all over again due to my poor planning. It won’t happen though. I think I got my fair dose of Persona for now. Instead I will touch some grass, play other things and write a review of this game (that I will release here when it’s ready).
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following my laundry list of games in progress, Mother 3 is the one I want to finish next. Hopefully it won’t take me as long, but I already had to spend some time grinding as this isn’t a particularly easy game. However, the humour, quirkiness and charm of it are keeping me invested on it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Sonic Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Action-adventure / Sega Dreamcast
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a huge Sonic fan since I started playing videogames, with the classic trilogy (&amp;amp; Knuckles) having a special place in my list of favourite games. Sonic Adventure on other hand, not so much. Every time I tried to play it in the past, I never got that far for one reason or another. This time I decided to give it a proper chance. Unfortunately, my opinion of Sonic’s first proper foray into 3D isn’t improving at all. The more I play, the less I understand why this game is taken in such high regards. But this is a story for another day and another review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for May! Next month I’ll try to bring more games to talk about, as if it was difficult. Without a time sucker like a Persona game, it’s likely to happen.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Here we are again, another month where almost all my playtime was absorbed by the same game. Luckily it was the last one! There was still some time to play a few more things, but not as many as I wanted. Anyway, here’s what I played in May:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phantasy Star</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/phantasy-star" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phantasy Star" /><published>2024-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/phantasy-star</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/phantasy-star">&lt;p&gt;Phantasy Star might be a name somewhat forgotten in today’s gaming landscape, but it had an important role in the conception of the Japanese role playing game subgenre, dominated nowadays by the likes of Final Fantasy, Dragon Quest, Persona, Yakuza and many others. In an era where video games were relatively quick and simple experiences, Phantasy Star pushed technological and storytelling boundaries in its medium.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-genesis-of-jrpgs&quot;&gt;In the Genesis of JRPGs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mid-80’s Sega was a very different company from what it is today. Their bread and butter was their arcade games, where they were able to constantly push the envelope in terms of graphical capabilities. Eager to bring that technological edge to the home consoles market, they released in Japan by 1985 the Sega Mark III, that would be later rebranded as Sega Master System on its international release in 1986. While technically superior to the popular Nintendo Entertainment System (also known as Famicom in Japan), its library of games was much smaller in comparison. Due to the lack of third party support, it was mostly up to Sega to bring new software for their system.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Following the success of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jmzHrNVelL0&quot;&gt;Dragon Quest&lt;/a&gt;, released exclusively for Nintendo, Sega decided to create their own RPG to capitalize on the recent interest in this genre and demonstrate once more their technical prowess. Composed by several talented programmers and designers, such as Yuki Naka and Naoto Ohshima (which would be later known for the creation of a certain game featuring a blue hedgehog), the development team had a clear goal - to outdo the competition in every way possible. A traditional medieval fantasy setting was discarded in favor of a story with sci-fi elements. Instead of one overworld with several locations, Phantasy Star had three explorable planets, with their own cities and biomes. The turn-based combat sections had much more detailed enemies and backgrounds than its contemporaries, such as the aforementioned Dragon Quest. Even the dungeons were a technical showcase, with a 3D first person perspective!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6hIwDZqiMD4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The Sega Ages version of Phantasy Star, the definitive way of playing this classic.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When it released, late in 1987, Phantasy Star had to share the spotlight with the very first Final Fantasy. Even though the later spawned arguably most iconic series of JRPGs ever, Phantasy Star was successful enough to receive three direct sequels on the Sega Mega Drive. The series still survives to this day, although in a MMORPG style, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pso2.com/&quot;&gt;Phantasy Star Online 2 New Genesis&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-took-ages-to-be-this-accessible&quot;&gt;It took ages to be this accessible&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative of this first Phantasy Star is set in the Algol star system, which comprises the planets Palma, Motavia, and Dezoris. The game starts precisely in Palma, with our protagonist, a girl named Alis, witnessing her brother’s death to the hands of the emperor Lassic’s troops. Right before dying he asks her to defeat Lassic, who’s leading their world to destruction. It’s with this motivation that Alis embarks on a journey to achieve that, alongside Odin, a typical strong fighter that wields axes and swords, Noah, your typical magician, and Myau, a yellow alien cat with supernatural powers. This party travels across the three planets to acquire the necessary equipment to defeat Lassic, while also attempting to uncover the truth behind his tyrannical regime by interacting with the natives of each planet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Although this sounds fun, there is one tiny problem. We are talking about a 37 years old game here, playing it in its original version nowadays is a true test of resilience. That’s where Sega Ages, a long running series of enhanced editions of classics from the company, comes to the rescue. The Sega Ages edition of Phantasy Star was released in 2018 exclusively for the Nintendo Switch, bringing a ton of quality-of-life features such as: dungeon maps, increased XP and money earned from each battle, reduced random encounters, faster walking speed and detailed items stats. Each feature individually makes a difference, but collectively, they transform a game nearly four decades old into a much more enjoyable experience today, allowing players to appreciate its merits without enduring many of the era’s typical pains. One crucial problem that wasn’t solved by this new version was the ability to accidentally ‘softlock’ our progress if we save the game in the wrong place without the right items. While Phantasy Star is a very linear game, it also doesn’t hold the player’s hand. As so, it’s surprisingly easy to miss any crucial if we don’t pay attention to the NPCs. I won’t lie, I didn’t do that and got lost quite easily. I resorted to a guide as soon as that happened. Even with this caveats, I think it was worth to experience this underappreciated classic.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remarkable graphics for 1987 standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interesting lore that mixes fantasy elements with sci-fi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sega Ages version makes the experience way more accessible for modern tastes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Way too linear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s easy to miss crucial elements and ‘softlock’ our progress
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good&quot;&gt;Good&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✧✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phantasy Star definetively deserves more recognition for its achievements in an era where the role-playing game genre was still in its infancy. While it was naturally outclassed in every aspect by many subsquent games, it’s still a worthwhile experience, specially in its Sega Ages version.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Phantasy Star might be a name somewhat forgotten in today’s gaming landscape, but it had an important role in the conception of the Japanese role playing game subgenre, dominated nowadays by the likes of Final Fantasy, Dragon Quest, Persona, Yakuza and many others. In an era where video games were relatively quick and simple experiences, Phantasy Star pushed technological and storytelling boundaries in its medium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Played this month – April 2024</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Played this month – April 2024" /><published>2024-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/played-this-month-apr-24">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, another month, another update. This time, as if two JRPGs weren’t enough, I decided to start (and luckily finish) one more. I even had to refrain myself from starting a fourth one. I’m clearly on my JPRG era, much like a teenager obsessed with My Chemical Romance, or whatever they listen these days. It will pass eventually, probably when I finish Persona 3 Reload.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Persona 3 Reload&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / PS4
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are, once again. I’m starting to run out of things to say about this game, as it makes by now three months since I started playing it. I’m definitely near its final, but from my experience with this series, that’s equivalent to no less than 20 hours of gameplay. At least its story it’s &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; getting interesting.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Mother 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / GBA
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another follow up from last month. I’m having a great time with it so far, with 10 hours clocked in by this point. The more I play it, the more I understand why it wasn’t released outside Japan. I have a feeling that current day Nintendo would never do a game like this. I will save the details for an eventual review.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Phantasy Star&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RPG / Sega Master System
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had some fascination for Sega’s oldest RPG series, but never had interest in actually playing the games before. That finally changed when I got the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6hIwDZqiMD4&quot;&gt;Sega Ages&lt;/a&gt; version of this Master System classic. This version, released for the Nintendo Switch, had a ton of quality of life features that made possible finishing it much faster than the original one. It’s surely a product of its time (and that time is 1987), but in terms of story and world building it’s still very fresh. While every other RPG of this era was focused solely on medieval fantasies, Phantasy Star took its inspiration from science fiction instead.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;u-mt-0 u-mb-1&quot;&gt;Streets of Rage 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beat’em’up / Sega Mega Drive
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the objective of giving more use to my Mega Drive, and eventually play Phantasy Star II, III and IV with rom hacks in the original hardware, I got an Everdrive, a cartridge that reads games from an SD card. I decided to test it with one of the best games for the system, Streets of Rage 2. Smashing delinquents to the sound of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pXLpubTPO94&quot;&gt;Yuzo Koshiro’s techno soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; is pure dopamine. Without even noticing, I finished it in one try.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all for April. For next month, I promise to bring fewer RPGs. See you next time!
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Hi everyone, another month, another update. This time, as if two JRPGs weren’t enough, I decided to start (and luckily finish) one more. I even had to refrain myself from starting a fourth one. I’m clearly on my JPRG era, much like a teenager obsessed with My Chemical Romance, or whatever they listen these days. It will pass eventually, probably when I finish Persona 3 Reload.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fallout (TV show)</title><link href="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fallout (TV show)" /><published>2024-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joaomarques.website/abxy/fallout-tv-show">&lt;p&gt;While I initially only envisioned reviewing video games in this space, I decided to make an exception for the Fallout TV show, that premiered recently on Amazon Prime Video. Since this show is set in the same universe as the games and is technically part of the story canon, a review here isn’t too out of place. I’m also taking the opportunity to talk about it while it’s still a hot topic. Keep in mind that even if this review isn’t spoiler heavy, I will mention some facts and events that you might want to discover by yourself, if you haven’t watched the TV show yet.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-vault-life&quot;&gt;A vault life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fallout universe is set in an alternate reality where nuclear bombs were massively deployed soon after World War II, profoundly affecting human scientific and technological advancements, culture, and the planet’s ecosystem. This led to the origin of the “wasteland”, where survival is the primary concern.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Away from the dire reality of the wasteland, a few selected individuals live in underground vaults spread across the United States. It’s precisely in one of this vaults that this show starts. We are quickly introduced to one of the main characters, Lucy, and to the busy life inside the vault 33, as the main goal of the vault dwellers - to repopulate the surface once the radiation levels are dissipated from it. However, things went terribly wrong for the inhabitants of Vault 33 when they were invaded and massacred by wastelanders, who also abducted Lucy’s father, the vault overseer, in the process. Lucy then decides to leave the vault for the first time in her life to find her father, echoing Fallout 3’s prologue.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There were still a lot of questions to answer regarding what happened in vault 33. Thankfuly the show does a great job on exploring the motivations behind such tragedy, as the mystery involving two other interconnected vaults, 31 and 32, conducted by the few survivors. Although this subplot was one of the most interesting parts of the show, it unfortunately remained unresolved. Let’s hope it has a follow up in season 2.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;c-post__img&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;c-post__video&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/V-mugKDQDlg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;❖ The trailer unveils the three main characters: Lucy, Maximus and Cooper.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-wasteland-journey&quot;&gt;The wasteland journey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already on the wasteland, Lucy’s path crosses with Maximus, a member of Brotherhood of Steel, a military order with the goal of control humanity’s most advanced technologies. Always mistreated inside the order, Maximus was sent on a mission to support a soldier retrieving a particular piece of technology. Unsurprisingly, the mission deviated from the plan, but Maximus gained the upper hand by seizing control of the soldier’s armor. Then we get the classic arc of the underdog that once it reaches the top, becomes what he despised the most. While not deal breaking for me, I just didn’t found his story interesting at all, specially because his realization comes really sudently and by the end he’s already the same old good natured underdog, but simply more powerful.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The third main character, who also crosses with Lucy during her journey, is in my opinion the most interesting one. Formerly a Hollywood actor and propaganda man for Vault-Tec, the company responsible for the underground vaults, Cooper Howard has since become a ghoul due to the devastating effects of the nuclear bombs. In this universe, ghouls are essentially people who got too much exposure to radiation, giving them a decomposed appearance, but also a much prolonged life span. During the entire season, our point of view from Cooper is constantly shifting between the past, before the bombing, and the present. What led him to accept doing advertisement for Vault-tec, oblivious of their obscure interests, and what made him eventually become the sour and ruthless ghoul he is.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Creating an original narrative and new characters was a winning choice from the showrunners. It gives something new for everyone, either long time fans or newcomers to the complex Fallout universe. What makes this show trully special however, is how they were able to capture perfectly the games’ essence, consisting of a mixture of dry (and sometimes dark) humor, some spectacularly gory scenes and a retro-futuristic aesthetic heavily inspired by the post-war America from the 40’s and 50’s.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fallout lore was used to perfection to build a brand new story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The series typical dry humor and ocasional gore are present here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A great introduction for newcomers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot of callbacks to the games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maximus story arc was a bit too cliché for my taste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vault 31, 32 and 33 mystery didn’t have a proper resolution
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great&quot;&gt;Great&lt;span class=&quot;u-ft-sans&quot;&gt;✦✦✦✦✧&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fallout, the TV show, joined the recent trend of great videogame adaptations, reviving the interest in a franchise that was dormant since the controversial release of Fallout 76. In case you have Amazon Prime, go watch it. In case you don’t, use a free trial. It’ll be worth, believe me.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">While I initially only envisioned reviewing video games in this space, I decided to make an exception for the Fallout TV show, that premiered recently on Amazon Prime Video. Since this show is set in the same universe as the games and is technically part of the story canon, a review here isn’t too out of place. I’m also taking the opportunity to talk about it while it’s still a hot topic. Keep in mind that even if this review isn’t spoiler heavy, I will mention some facts and events that you might want to discover by yourself, if you haven’t watched the TV show yet.</summary></entry></feed>